<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain discourse shewing how we are to walk after the Lord's Supper necessary for every communicant. From I Col. 10. That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing. Being the substance of several sermons preached to a congregation in Hatton-Garden. By John Horsman, an unworthy servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Horsman, John, fl. 1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2871A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219052</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830588</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2092:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain discourse shewing how we are to walk after the Lord's Supper necessary for every communicant. From I Col. 10. That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleasing. Being the substance of several sermons preached to a congregation in Hatton-Garden. By John Horsman, an unworthy servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Horsman, John, fl. 1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 146 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for E. Richardson, at the Naked Boy in Blowbladder-Street, over against St. Martins le Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page on A2.</note>
                  <note>Running title: How we are to walk after the Lord's Supper.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians I --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain Diſcourſe Shewing how we are to WALK After the <hi>Lord's Supper:</hi> Neceſſary for every <hi>Communicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>From 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 10.</bibl>
               <p>That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Being the Subſtance of Several Sermons. Preached to a Congregation in <hi>Hatton-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Horſman,</hi> an unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Vivimus, non loquimur, magna.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Richardſon,</hi> at the <hi>Naked Boy</hi> in <hi>Blowbladder-Street,</hi> over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt St. <hi>Martins le Grand.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35041:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35041:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Serious Reader.</head>
            <p>IT was not without great conflict and ſtrugling within my ſelf, that this comes forth into Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick View, being very ſenſible of my great unfitneſs for ſuch an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; for tho', as one ſays, the plain thread bare ſuit may do well enough at home, yet when perſons go abroad a better habit is required and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. But ſuch as have not this change of Apparel muſt be content with what they have.</p>
            <p>If it be the bravery and gaudery of Language that thou expectest in the following Diſcourſe, thy expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations will be fruſtrated; for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſuch a garb might ſuit the
<pb facs="tcp:35041:3"/>airy humour of the Age, yet it would no ways be agreeable or ſuteable to the weightyneſs and gravity of the Subject treated on, which is not to ſhow how we may pleaſe Men, but how we may pleaſe God, how we may walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing. I am not unſenſible that this Piece will fall into divers and different hands, and according to the hands it falls into, ſuch will be the Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it muſt expect. By the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane it is probable it will be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided. For to ſuch as have no ſenſe, nor reliſh, nor ſavour of Spiritual Things and Serious Matters, ſuch things as theſe are will be the Object of their Scorn and Deriſion, with whom the deep things of God are counted no better than Myſterious Nonſenſe. And whatever hath but the Face and Shew of Seriouſneſs, with ſuch it is accounted Canting, and Affected Singularity. By the Curious, and Captious, it is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:35041:3"/>probable it will be deſpiſed; becauſe ſuch will not meet with that exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and accuracy of Method and Stile, with thoſe flights and ſtrains of Rhetorick which is moſt pleaſing, and grateful to this ſort. By the Learned it alſo may be but little ſet by, becauſe they will not find a Margin filled with Quotations of Fathers and Schoolmen, nor with the Sayings of <hi>Poets</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi> It may poſſibly paſs for a Plain, Honest, Well-meaning-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. And indeed were it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it would not Anſwer its <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> nor would it be ſo ſuited to that ſort of Reader for which it was chiefly and principally deſigned, <hi>viz. The Serious Reader.</hi> For ſuch it was chiefly deſign'd, and to ſuch it is humbly Dedicated. Whatever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it may have with others, yet I hope it may be as Manna, ſweet to the Taſt of all ſerious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. How weak ſoever the manner
<pb facs="tcp:35041:4"/>of handling this Subject is, yet the Subject it ſelf is very weighty and ſeaſonable. The Duty preſs'd to is very neceſſary, but too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. We are ready to take up with the Theory of Religion, and the Speculative part of Piety, but are too great Strangers to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical part thereof. We may know many things, and believe many things, but yet if we do not put into Practice the things that we know and believe, we only have a name to live, but yet are dead. We have only a form of Godlineſs, but are ſtrangers to the Life and Power of it. We are for Reading and Studying, and Hearing of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but the Apostle <hi>James</hi> his Advice is, Not to be Hearers of the Word only, but Doers of the Word alſo, <hi>1 Jam. 22.</hi> The Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Power and Life of Religion lies in the Practice of it. It is not enough that we make a Profeſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:35041:4"/>that we are taken into Church-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and Partake of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Goſpel, unleſs we do adorn this Profeſſion with a ſutea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and agreeable Walk, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, according to that advice of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, 1 Phil. 27. Only let your Converſation be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> The neglect of this among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſars of this Age, is very much to be lamented and bewailed. Now to quicken and direct us herein is the main drift and tendency of the following Diſcourſe. And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, how we are to Walk after that Great Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi> I hope it will not be judged to be altogether needleſs, nor prove altogether uſeleſs. And that it may not be altogether fruitleſs and ſucceſsleſs, I commend both thee and it to the Divine Benediction, which crowns all our Labours, and gives Succeſs to all our Lawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours.
<pb facs="tcp:35041:5"/>Paul <hi>may plant, and</hi> Apollos <hi>water, but it is God that giveth the increaſe; for neither is he that planteth any thing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that watereth any thing, but God that giveth the increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Thine in our Bleſſed Lord, <hi>J. Horſman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35041:5"/>
            <head>A PLAIN DISCOURSE, SHEWING, How we are to WALK after the Lord's Supper.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>From 1 Col. 10.</bibl>
               <q>That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words are the Matter of the Apoſtles Prayer for theſe <hi>Colloſſians.</hi> In two things, among others, the Apoſtle did expreſs and demonſtrate his great love to them. The firſt was, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Thanks for them. The Second was, in Praying for them. He gave Thanks for them, and he Prayed for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35041:6"/>them, v. 3. <hi>We give thanks to God, and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, praying always for you.</hi> Now the matter of his Thankfulneſs for them he refers to Two Heads.
<list>
                  <item>1. Their Graces.</item>
                  <item>2. The Means by which they are wrought.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Their Graces, which were chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Three, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith, Hope and Love. Their Faith by the Object. Their Love by the Extent. Their Hope by the Place, v. 4. <hi>Since we heard of your faith in Christ Jeſus,</hi> there is the Object of their Faith; <hi>and of the love which ye have to all the Saints,</hi> there is the Extent of their Love; <hi>and for the hope which is laid up for you in Heaven,</hi> there is the place of their Hope.</p>
            <p>The Means by which theſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were wrought, which was the Word, from <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. Thus much for the Matter of his Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. The Matter of his Prayer
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35041:6"/>for them was this, viz. <hi>That they might be filled with the knowledge of Gods will, in all wiſdom and ſpiritual underſtanding, that they might walk worthy of the Lord to all pleaſing, being fruitful in every good work, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in the knowledge of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence we may take notice of this by the way, that next to our own good and welfare, we ought to rejoyce at, and be concerned for, the good and welfare of others.</p>
            <p>Thus it was with this bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. He was not only thankful to God for his goodneſs to himſelf in particular, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.12, 13. But he is thankful for Gods for goodneſs unto others. <hi>We give thanks to God and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Christ, for your faith in Christ, and for your love which ye have to all the Saints, and for the hope which is laid up for you in heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And then, ſhews himſelf greatly concerned for their good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, in praying always for them.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35041:7"/>
               <hi>For this cauſe we alſo ſince we heard of it, do not ceaſe to pray for you,</hi> v. 9.</p>
            <p>See what concernedneſs he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts and expreſſes for his Brethren his Kinſmen according to the fleſh, Rom. 9.1, 2, 3. <hi>I ſay the truth, I lie not, my conſcience bearing me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the Holy Ghoſt, that I have great heaviness and continual ſorrow in my heart, for I could wiſh my ſelf accurſed from Chriſt, for my Brethren my Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men according to the fleſh.</hi> It is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange expreſſion, but it notes his zeal, and affection, and concerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their good and welfare. Rom. 10.1. <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they may be ſaved.</hi> It is a great ſign that Grace hath taken hold of our hearts, when we are really concerned for the good of others, that the ſame Grace that hath taken hold of us, may take hold of others too. <hi>By this,</hi> ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>John, we know that we are paſsd from death to life becauſe we love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14. And truly our love
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35041:7"/>to others cannot be more fully expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and truly demonſtrated, than by an affectionate concernment for their ſpiritual good and welfare. If they be wholly ignorant of God and Chriſt, that they may be brought to a ſaving knowledge of God and Chriſt: Or if they be ſuch as have been in any meaſure brought to a ſaving knowledge of God, then that there may be a dayly increaſe of it. And this was the Apoſtles Prayer for theſe <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> having heard of their Faith in Chriſt, and their Love to the Saints, and their Knowledge of God, he prays that they may be filled with it in a dayly encreaſe of it for a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Faith in Chriſt, and for a farther increaſe in the Knowledge of God. He is not, you ſee, of a little narrow, private ſpirit, ſwallowed up in his own private concernments, but of a brave noble generous ſpirit, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his deſires and endeavours, not only to his own good, but to the good of others too. And this is one cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35041:8"/>and property of a gracious Soul, of a ſanctifyed perſon, that he is full of conſtant and ardent deſires after the good and welfare of others. The manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every Member to profit withall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. Religious love ſeeketh not her own things. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. We ſhould not ſeek our own things as many do, but the things which are Jeſus Chriſt's, <hi>viz.</hi> that which tends to his Glory, and the Good of his Members. Chriſtians ſhould ſerve one another by Love. Certainly what a Man is in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he is relatively ſo. If not fit to ſerve the Body, than not fit to be of the Body. He is no Saint that ſeeks not the Communion of Saints. Having taken notice of this by the way, I come now to the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>In which words we have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Apoſtle's Deſire and Prayer for them, but we may alſo read our own Duty in them, and that is to walk
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35041:8"/>worthy of the Lord unto all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. This is the end of all our Knowledge of God and his will, which in the 9th <hi>verſe</hi> he deſired they might be filled with. Why filled with the Knowledge of God's Will? Why, <hi>That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing.</hi> To this end we ſhould be filled with the Knowledge of God's Will, that our Converſations may be rightly ordered to the Glory of God, that our Lives may anſwer the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we make, and the Knowledge we have obtain'd, and the Mercies we receive, and the Means we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> would find Merit of Works in this Verſe. Both becauſe holineſs of Life is ſo much urged by it; And alſo becauſe here is the word <hi>Worthy</hi> uſed; as if the Apoſtle ſhould grant that they might be worthy of, or Merit the Bleſſings of God.</p>
            <p>Now to this might be returned a Two-fold. Anſwer.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35041:9"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That <hi>Merit</hi> cannot be founded upon Scripture.</item>
                  <item>2. That it cannot be founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Scripture.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>First.</hi> It cannot be founded upon Scripture. The Scripture doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly and in many places de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt it. It cuts off and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all glorying and boaſting in our ſelves, as if by our worthineſs we could procure any thing of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at the hands of God, or by our goodneſs any way recommend our ſelves to the favour and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of God. You ſee your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Brethren, <hi>how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called, for God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe,</hi> &amp;c. And all this that no fleſh ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his preſence. <hi>But he that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth let him glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35041:9"/>1.26, 27, 28. Alas, we are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to the Divine Bounty and Goodneſs that gave us our beings both in Nature and Grace, that when we have done all we can, we are forced to acknowledge, <hi>that we are unprofitable ſervants,</hi> Luk. 17.10. Whatever good we do it is from God, and therefore cannot Merit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at the hands of God. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. So ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency it is of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 4.10. <hi>For who maketh thee to differ from another? And what hast thou that thou haſt not received? Now if thou didſt receive it, Why doſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it?</hi> Were there no other Scriptures, theſe were ſufficient to overthrow the Notion ef Merit</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor can it be founded upon this Scripture. This expreſſion of walking worthy of the Lord cannot
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35041:10"/>be applied to Merit by any means, in as much as the Lord had beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many of his Bleſſings and Favours and Benefits already. They cannot by any good Works afterward, be ſaid any ways to Merit what is paſt; now it is very abſurd to think, that we can by any after good Works Merit what was given us before. But we will paſs by this and come to the true meaning of this expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>To walk worthy of the Lord, is no more than to walk ſuitably and agreeably, and ſome way anſwerably and becomingly to the many-fold Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of God vouchſafed to us; which will be better underſtood by comparing it with the parallel places, Eph. 4.1. <hi>I therefore the Priſoner of the Lord beſeech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called.</hi> Walk worthy of your vocation, that is, anſwerably and ſuitably and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming your Calling, as appears by the following words, which fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35041:10"/>it, viz. <hi>With all lowlineſs, and meekneſs, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love,</hi> &amp;c. This is ſuch a kind of Walking as is becoming and agreeable to our High and Holy Calling, Phil. 1.27. <hi>only let your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> This is the true meaning and explication of this Expreſſion of walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthy. He means no more by it than this, a becoming walk, or a ſuitable walk, <hi>but let your Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be worthy of the Goſpel of Christ.</hi> So in the 1 Theſ. 2.12. <hi>That you would walk worthy of God who ha h called you into his Kingdom and Glory.</hi> It is the ſame word in the original in all theſe places, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is in the forquoted place rendered <hi>becoming, Let your Converſation be as becometh the Goſpel. Let your Converſation be worthy of the Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>becoming the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> So here, walking worthy of God is no more than walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuitably to the Nature of that God who is the true and living God.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35041:11"/>That ye may walk like a People that are taken into Covenant with God, and expreſs the Virtues and Praiſes of him who hath called you out of Darkneſs into his marvelous Light, in your Lives and Converſations; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which we have in the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Ye are a choſen genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a royal prieſthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people, that you ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him who hath called you out of darkneſs into his marvellous light.</hi> Or that ye ſhould walk ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to this great Mercy and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Priviledges and Benefits ye have received from him. So that to walk worthy of the Lord, is to live and behave our ſelves as becometh thoſe to whom God hath vouchſafed ſo great a Mercy, that paſſing by many Thouſands of a nobler extraction, of a ſweeter diſpoſition, and in many outward reſpects better than we. That he ſhould out of his meer Grace and Love in Chriſt, chuſe and call us out of the World to be partakers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35041:11"/>of Eternal Life with him. That he ſhould take us and leave others, chuſe us and paſs by others, as it is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and aſtoniſhing, ſo it ought to influence us into a walking ſome way ſuitable and becoming theſe great Mercies beſtowed upon us. And if we would know what this ſuitable walking is? why the next words explain it; It is a walking unto all pleaſing, ſo that the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That where a Perſon or a People receive great Mercys, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, or Priviledges from God, there ought to be a ſuitable, anſwerable, and becoming walking thereunto; or thus, It ought to be our ſtudy and endeavour to live and act ſuitably and becoming the Mercies and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours we receive from God.</p>
            <p>God hath dealt Bountifully and Graciouſly with us, remembered us not only with Common and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but with Special and Spiritual Mercys too. Do we enjoy Peace
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35041:12"/>and Quietneſs, when many other are involved in great Troubles and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities? Is Plenty and Fulneſs our Inheritance, when Scarcity and Want is the lot of many others? Do we enjoy ſuch a competency of Health and Strength, when many others are Sick and weak, Languiſhing and Dying? Hath God ſet any of us at Liberty from our Confinements, wrought out a Recovery for any of us from any tedious and dangerous Diſtemper, which detained us from waiting and attending upon God in the Publick and Solemn Dutys of his Worſhip, when many others are ſtill confined to their Chambers, and many to their Beds? How doth it concern ſuch to walk anſwerably and ſuitably to the Mercies they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Let ſuch remember that advice of our Saviour to the man upon whom he had wrought a great cure, John. 5.14. <hi>And he ſaid unto him go thy way, behold thou art made whole, ſin no more leſt a worſe thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35041:12"/>
            <p>God hath done great things for us, and in ſome reſpects for all of us; In bearing ſo long with our renewed and repeated Provocations, inſomuch that we are under a neceſſity of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging and confeſſing that it is of the Lords Mercys we were not conſumed, that our Bodies are not in the ſilent Grave, and our Souls roaring in Hell; That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all our Barrenneſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſs under the means and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Grace, that yet the day and ſeaſon of Grace ſhould be lengthned out to us; that after ſo many denyals and refuſals, Chriſt ſhould ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to knock at the door of our Hearts. That when we have ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently turned a deaf Ear to the calls and invitations of Chriſt in the Goſpel, that he ſhould ſtill continue to call and invite, and promiſeth a kind Reception and hearty Welcome to all thoſe that will come unto him. That he ſhould ſtill continue wooing and beſeeching us by his Miniſters
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35041:13"/>and Ambaſſadors to be reconciled unto God, after our ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in ways of Enmity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him. O the Patience, Long-ſuffering and Forbearance of God! that ever he ſhould ſo long put up the affronts and indignitys that are every day offered to his Bleſſed Majeſty, by ſuch crawling Worms of the Earth, bear ſo long with the Rebellions and Ingratitudes of his Creatures! Lord how good art thou to the worſt of Men, and the vileſt of Sinners? in ſparing and forbearing them, in protecting and providing for them, in calling and inviting them, in waiting to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to them, in offering Mercy and Pardon, and Grace and Chriſt to them, in affording them time and ſpace and opportunity for Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and turning unto God, in vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeing to them many Temporal Bleſſings and Favours in the midſt and face of ſuch dayly Provocations, and abuſe of his Bounties. Thus I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35041:13"/>ſay in ſome reſpects God is good to us all, and hath done great things for us all, even for the worſt and vileſt Sinner now in his Preſence. And to ſome of us he hath been more peculiarly and ſpecially and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhingly good, In chuſing and calling us not only by the outward call of his Word, but by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and effectual call of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, out of darkneſs unto light, and from the power of Sin, and Self, and Satan, and the World, to Himſelf; out of a ſtate of Nature, unto his Kingdom and Glory; unto his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace here, and in a little time longer will call us to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Glory. In Juſtifying us freely by his Grace, and Sanctifying us by his Holy Spirit throughout, and adopting us into his Family. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering us in our low and loſt eſtate and condition, when we were blind and naked, and wretched and miſerable, caſt out into the open field to the loathing of our Perſons,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35041:14"/>in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of Iniquity, held in the ſnare of the Devil and led captive by him at his pleaſure, under the power and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of many vile Luſts and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; in bondage and ſlavery to Sin and Satan; ſubjected and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrawl'd to Death; under the Wrath and Curſe of God; liable to all the miſeries of this Life, and to the pains of Hell for ever; ignorant of God and Chriſt, and Spiritual things, nay enemies to God and Chriſt, nay enmity it ſelf. When we were in ſuch a forlorn, helpleſs and miſerable ſtate and condition as this, he pittyed us, and helped us; when none other eye pittyed us, nay, when we had no pitty for our ſelves he pittyed us, and helped us when none other could help us. Others paſſed by us and took no notice of us, but he looked upon us, and behold it was a time of Love with us. He threw his Skirt over us and covered our Nakedneſs, and poured Water upon us to waſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35041:14"/>away our filthineſs. He Swear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and entred into Covenant with us to be ours, and we to be his; he to be our God, and we to be his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar People. He hath given Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his Son, his spirit to us. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be our God and Portion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33. <hi>But this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with the Houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe days ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law into their hearts, and write it in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</hi> And what Tongue can expreſs? What Pen can deſcribe the happineſs of that People who have God to be their God? <hi>David</hi> in the 144 <hi>Pſalm, v.</hi> 15. ſays, <hi>Happy are the People whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> He doth not ſay how happy, for it is beyond expreſs. But this we may truly ſay, that all our happineſs and felicity, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, lies in this, in having God to be our God. If there be no want to them that fear God, I am ſure
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35041:15"/>there can be none to them that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God, who is a Soul-comforting, Soul-refreſhing, Soul-ſatisfying Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. It matters not what our Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Conditions are here in this World, be they never ſo low, and inconſiderable, if we have but God for our God we are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. <hi>Happy is that People whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> He hath given us not only himſelf, but his Son too, John 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him for us. To obey and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, to bleed and dye, and ſuffer and ſatisfy for us, to reſcue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us from thoſe evils and miſeries under which we lay, <hi>viz.</hi> the Wrath of God, the Curſe of the Law, by laying down his life for us, a life more precious than the lives of all the Angels in Heaven, or Men upon Earth.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35041:15"/>
            <p>Not only given him for us, but given him to us, to be believed in, and reſted upon, for Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to dwell in us, and be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to us; to be made of God Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Redemption; to be to us, and do for us all that God hath appointed and deſigned him to be.</p>
            <p>Again, he hath not only given us himſelf, and Son, but his Spirit alſo to us. To open our Eyes, to enlighten our Minds, to incline our Wills, to change our Hearts, to Turn and Convert us to himſelf, To convince of Sin, to lead to Chriſt, to be the guid of our ways, to be the death of our ſins, to quicken and enliven and ſtrengthen our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. To witneſs with our ſpirits that we are the Children of God. To comfort us in all our Troubles, to ſuccour us in all our Temptations, to reſolve us in all our Doubts, to help us againſt all our Infirmities. To conduct us ſafe through this evil
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35041:16"/>World, and to ſeal us up to the day of Redemption.</p>
            <p>But yet farther, he gives us liberty to wait upon him in the ſolemn Dutys of his Worſhip. He gives us Praying ſeaſons, and Hearing ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Communicating ſeaſons, for the carrying on begun Grace in our Souls. Thus richly doth he furniſh our Table in this howling Deſart, and bountifully provides for us in a ſtrange Land. We have not only Food for our Bodies, but Food for our Souls, not only the Bread that periſheth, but that which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures to Everlaſting Life. The Lamb is ſlain and behold all things are ready. The Marriage Supper is prepared, and a welcome ready for all that come to it. This is Chriſt's language to all his gueſts, O friends drink ye, eat <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, drink and eat abundantly O beloved. And what do you think is the matter of this Feaſt? Why it is Chriſt with all his ſaving Benefits, even Peace
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35041:16"/>and Pardon and Comfort. This is the Goſpel Feaſt unto which poor Sinners are invited. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is both the maſter and the matter of this Feaſt. This is that Bread which came down from Heaven, which is othergates Food than that Manna was which fell in the Wilderneſs, of which it is ſaid, <hi>Our Fathers did eat and they are dead, but whoſoever eateth of this Bread lives for ever,</hi> John 6.48, 49, 50. This is the Lamb that was ſlain from the Foundations of the World, whoſe Fleſh is Meat indeed and whoſe Blood is Drink indeed.</p>
            <p>Thus bountifully hath God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for our Souls, we have not only the ſincere Milk of the Word that we may grow thereby, but more ſubſtantial Food, even that ſealing, ſtrengthening, confirming Ordinance of the Lords Supper, where Chriſt and all his Benefits are repreſented ſealed and applied to Belivers, who was not only offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35041:17"/>up upon the Croſs for the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Divine Juſtice and the expiation of our Sins, but offered up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Table for the ſatisfying our guilty minds and for the Food and Nouriſhment of our Souls. Here it is that we may take a view of Chriſt's dying love. Here we ſee him Bruiſed and Broken and Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for our ſakes and for our Sins. Here we may ſee him broken and bruiſed by his Father in the day of his great Wrath, when his Body was torn, his Soul in a dreadful Agony, his ſide pierced, his Blood ſhed; theſe are in a moſt lively manner repreſented by the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Bread, and pouring out of the Wine. Here is a Wounded, Broken, Bleeding, Jeſus repreſented to us. The Elements in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſignifie, and ſet forth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Sufferings of our bleſſed Lord, both in his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody and in his Soul. The Bread ſignifies the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of his Body. And the Wine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35041:17"/>which is a repreſentation of his Blood, the Agonvs of his Soul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirits whereby the Soul acts are in the Blood.</p>
            <p>All the Sacraments that ever were inſtituted ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall to this very day, both ordinary and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, both Old Teſtament and New Teſtament Sacraments, they all of them principally repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and point at Jeſus and him Crucified. <hi>Adams</hi> Sacrifices were Types of Chriſt the true Sacrifice. Circumciſion a pledge of our Hearts Circumciſion thro' Chriſts Blood, Col. 2.11. <hi>In whom alſo ye are Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the Body of the Sins of the Fleſh by the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of Chriſt.</hi> The Paſſover was a token and Type of Chriſt our Paſſover Sacrificed for us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. Baptiſm, this doth point at the Death of Chriſt, we are ſaid by Baptiſm to be Baptiſed into Chriſt, and into his Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35041:18"/>And the Lords Supper is a moſt lively repreſentation of the Death of Chriſt, 1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup ye ſhew the Lords death till he come.</hi> This is a ſtanding memorial and a laſting monument of our bleſſed Lords love in bleeding and dying for us, and is to continue to the end of the World, even till the coming of our Lord to Judgment. So that Chriſt and his Death, Chriſt as Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, is that which is repreſented and pointed at in this Sacrament. Here it is that Chriſt Jeſus is as it were afreſh Crucified before our eyes, bruiſed by his Father, pierced by the Souldiers, bleeding for our ſins. Here is a ſweet love-token in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed betwixt Chriſt and his Church, betwixt Chriſt and Believers. What greater love can be imagined than to dye for us. <hi>Greater love hath no man than this that a man lay down his life for his friend.</hi> Ay but here was greater love than this, here was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35041:18"/>Blood ſhed and a Life laid down for very Enemies. This Ordinance may truly be ſtiled a Love Feaſt. Every thing in it ſpeaks love. The Myſteries in it ſpeak love. Here is Chriſt's Body not whole but broken, Chriſt's Blood not in his veins, but ſhed and freely poured out for poor ſinners. The benefits intended to us by it ſpeak great love. Here is compleat Proviſion and full Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our Souls, for our Faith and all the graces of the inward man intended by it. A freſh ſeal of the Pardon of our Sins in the Blood of Chriſt. Fuller and clearer diſcoverys of God's reconciled face in and thro the Attoning Blood of the Lord Jeſus, that Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant. A more full confirmation and a more cloſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the New Covenant and all the Promiſes, Comforts, Benefits and Priviledges thereof to our Souls, and a more full Communion with Chriſt in his Grace and fullneſs, in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35041:19"/>his Death and Sufferings, in his great Undertakings, and glorious Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions, in his high Dignitys and Relations, in his great Victorys and Atchievements, and in thoſe neceſſary offices of Prophet, Prieſt, and King to his Church, theſe are ſome of the great benefits that are intended to us by this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Now we that have been ſo lately entertained at this Table of the Lord, that have or might have been feaſting and ſatiateing our Souls upon this Banquet of Chriſts love; it behooves and concerns every one of us to walk worthy of the Lord unto all-pleaſing, to walk worthy of this love of Chriſt in doing and ſuffering, in bleeding and dying for us. That is, to walk ſuitably and ſome way becoming thoſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love that have been exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and repreſented to us in this Ordinance. I ſay it highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every one of us, who have been feaſting at this Banquet of Chriſts
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35041:19"/>love, it concerns us to keep up and maintain a ſuitable and becoming walk after it. Remembring that it is not enough to Eat and Drink worthily at this Supper, but we muſt alſo walk worthily after this Supper: we have oftentimes bills put up for a prepared heart and a ſuitable frame, that perſons may come prepared to this Ordinance of the Lords Supper, that they may not eat and drink unworthily. But I do not remember that ever I ſaw a bill for a ſuitable walk and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour afterward. It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that we duely prepare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, act worthily in, but we muſt alſo walk ſuitably after Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating. And there is as much need to put up a Prayer, and to diſpatch a cry to Heaven, that we may walk worthily after, as well as come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredly to this Supper. By walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthily I mean no more than walking ſuitably and becomingly.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35041:20"/>
            <p>But here it may be asked what is this ſuitable walking? or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth it conſiſt? or how is it that we are to walk after this Supper Ordinance? To this we ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
<list>
                  <item>I. More Generally.</item>
                  <item>II. More Particularly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="general_considerations">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p> The general anſwer to this is, more Holily; after this Supper of the Lord we are to walk more Holily. Now to this holy walking there muſt be a Principle of Grace wrought in the heart. I ſay, before there can be any holineſs in the life, we muſt firſt ſuppoſe that there be Grace in the heart. A perſon muſt be holy before his actions can be holy. For till a Man be Regenerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and act from a Principle of Grace in his heart, all he doth is but the ſhadow and imperfect imiation of a good action, as an Ape would
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35041:20"/>imitate a Man, or as an artificial motion doth reſemble that which is natural. Grace muſt firſt be infuſed to beget life, and then we are viſibly to expreſs it in a courſe of godly walking. And then there muſt not be only a Principle from which we muſt walk, but there muſt be a Rule by which we muſt walk, and that is the Law or Word of God, which meets and ſets out the bounds of Sin and Duty, which tells us what evil we are to decline, and ſhun, and what good we are to proſecute and perſue. Now there is a twofold Holineſs.
<list>
                     <item>Internal and</item>
                     <item>External.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>Internal,</label>
                     <item>which lies in the hatred of ſin, and a love of that which is good.</item>
                     <label>External,</label>
                     <item>and that is expreſſed in avoiding of the one, and perſuing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35041:21"/>after the other.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now this Holy Walk doth conſiſt, in a careful avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is evil and ſinful, and in an eager perſuite after that which is good. It hath two parts.
<list>
                     <item>The one Privative,</item>
                     <item>The other Poſſitive.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>The Privative part</label>
                     <item>which is called Mortification or a dying to ſin.</item>
                     <label>The Poſſitive part</label>
                     <item>which is called Vivification or a living unto Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eousneſs.</item>
                  </list>
The one is the purging out of Sin, the other is the ſpiritual refining of the Soul. The one is a ceaſing to do evil, the other is a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do well. The one is a ſtrenuous oppoſition of Sin, the other is a vigorous exerciſe of all Grace.</p>
               <p>Now after this Supper Ordinance we are to walk more Holily. To hate ſin more than ever, and to love God and Chriſt, and the things that are ſpiritually good more than ever.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35041:21"/>To dye more unto Sin, and to live more unto Righteouſneſs. It is true we cannot be more Elected, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more juſtified, after Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating than we were before. But we may and ought to be more ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified than before. Sanctification is a progreſſive thing; it is compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſeed that grows, firſt the blade ſprings up, then the ear, then the ripe Corn. We are not ſo much ſanctified but we may be more ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. We do not walk ſo holily but we may walk more holily ſtill, there is none ſo good, but he may be better, 2 Cor. 7.1. <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes, dearly beloved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord.</hi> So I may ſay having theſe love Banquets, theſe Sacrament ſeaſons, and Supper Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, dearly beloved, time after time returning upon us, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting. Holineſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35041:22"/>in the fear of the Lord. Tho' Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication doth not admit of Degrees, yet Sanctification doth, that is ſtill encreaſing like the ſhining light, or Morning Sun, that ſhines more and more, and brighter and brighter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perfect Day, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. and ſhould be daily growing more and more in Knowledge, in Faith in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, in Love, in all Grace and Conſolation, until all be perfected and ſwallowed up in Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="particular_considerations">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>More particularly. And we may take the Anſwer in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing things, which indeed are but branches of the other; but for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Memory ſake, I chuſe to put them into ſo many Particulars. As,</p>
               <div n="1" type="particular">
                  <p>1. More Watchfully and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly. After Communicating, there muſt be a watchful circumſpect walking. As a Man that hath a Treaſure in his houſe is very watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35041:22"/>and careful leaſt he be robbed of it. Now it is to be ſuppoſed, and hoped, that we have received that in the participation of that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which the Devil would be glad to deprive us of. Whatever comfort and refreſhment we have had, whatever Aſſurances and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of Gods Love we have had a-new and a-freſh; whatever lights of Chriſt, and reſolutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin we have had, he ſtands ready to undoe all that hath been done, and to deprive us of all that we got. Upon this account we have need to walk watchfully and circumſpectly. We had need to have our eyes upward, and our eyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and our eyes round about us. Did we find, through Grace, our hearts wrought up to any gracious frames? Did we find that our Souls were refreſhed, that our hearts were inlarged, that our affections were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed to Chriſt, that we received any virtue from, and had communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35041:23"/>with Chriſt? Did we make freſh vows and reſolutions, that through the Grace of Chriſt enabling us, we would walk before him in holyneſs and newneſs of life all our days? Why then we may depend upon it, and look for it, that the Devil will be very buſy to undoe all this. We muſt expect that he will have a fling at us; for he is never more bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy in tempting, then when we have been Worſhipping. He is never more buſy in Tempting us to ſin, then after we have been making new and freſh reſolutions againſt ſin. When we have been at the Lord's Table renewing our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants with God, and eſtabliſhing our reſolutions of better Obedience: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe things the Devil will come with all his forces and endeavours to make us break our Vows, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect our Covenants. He will be courting us to return to our old ſins, and our old frames, to our coldneſs and deadneſs, and lukewarmneſs,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35041:23"/>and worldly-mindedneſs, to our fears and doubtings, to our old manner and courſe of living. Therefore we had need to walk watchfully and circumſpectly, watching our words, thoughts, actions, lives and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, that we do not return to our old vain light frothy converſations, that better becomes the Prophane than the Profeſſor. The liberty that ſome do allow themſelves this way, Communicants I mean, in frothy, I had almoſt ſaid, in filthy Diſcourſes, and unſeemly Actions, is a thing that is much to be lamented and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed in our day. It is a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to diſtinguiſh the profeſſing from the carnal part of the World, who are very near as airy in their Dreſſes as light and frothy in their Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and as vain in their converſations as the Carnal Crew. And is this a walk becoming thoſe who ſit down at their Lord's Table? O no: ſuch ought to walk very watchfully and circumſpectly, that they may not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35041:24"/>the ways of God and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be reproached and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. We had need walk watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that we do not loſe thoſe ſights of Chriſt, thoſe comforts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments, thoſe enlargements and enjoyments that we had in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. That the fellowſhip and communion we had with Chriſt be not quickly interrupted and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. It is a great miſtake in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to think, that when the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is ended, their Work is ended; that they have nothing more to do, nor nothing farther to mind, as if now they might return to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer courſes again, and be as vain and worldly, and wicked as before. It is to be feared this is the practice of too many Communicants in our day, that no ſooner, or ſoon after the action is over, they return to their old courſe of ſinning; Receive the Sacrament one day, and may be, be Drunk before the next; nay, it may be, have their Oaths and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35041:24"/>in their Mouths, before the Bread and Wine is well out of their Mouths. It were well, if that which was laid unto <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Charge, might not be laid to the charge of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Communicants in our day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.6. <hi>The people ſat down to eat and drink, and roſe up to play.</hi> O how many ſit down at the Lord's Table to eat and drink of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Elements, and riſe up to play, return again to their old courſes, playing and ſporting and fooling with ſin, to their Curſing and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Sabbath-breaking, to their Adultery, Uncleanneſs, Injuſtice, Drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c. Like the Dog to his vomit and the Sow when ſhe is waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> Thus do many return again to their former luſts and ſins, with as great nay greater ſtrength than ever, ſo mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves twofold more the Children of hell than before. There ought to he a mighty careful, heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, circumſpect, watchful walking
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35041:25"/>after we have been at the Table of the Lord remembring that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental efficacy and bond doth not oblige us for a day only or a week only, but it binds us for our whole lives. But to conclude what I intend to ſay upon this head, was it the ſincere and earneſt deſire of our Souls before we came to this Ordinance that we might bring ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able frames and affection; to it, and did the Lord anſwer our crys here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? why now we ought to be as careful and as much concerned that thoſe gracious frames of heart may be maintained and kept up in our Souls. Did we beg to come with bleeding and broken hearts to this Ordinance? why now it is our duty to beg that they may be kept bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and broken. Did we beg for a ſtronger Faith? for more glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burning affections to this loving lovely Jeſus? why now we are to watch and pray againſt unbelief, againſt coldneſs and luke-warmneſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35041:25"/>of love and affection. Did we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to forſake our Sins? why now we are to watch more narrowly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and to beg of God ſtrength and Grace that thoſe purpoſes and intentions may be forthwith put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to execution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="particular">
                  <p>2. More Humbly, entertaining low and mean thoughts and opinions of our ſelves, acknowledging our own baſeneſs and vileneſs, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and unworthineſs, loathing and abhorring our ſelves under a ſenſe of our daily weakneſſes, and ſinful Infirmities, renouncing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting all Righteouſneſs of our own as being altogether inſufficient any ways to recommend us to the Divine Love and Favour, looking upon our ſelves as loathſome and odious and no way lovely and amiable in the fight of God, accuſing, judging and condemning our ſelves, owning and admiring and adoring free Love and free Grace in all that Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35041:26"/>hath done for us, and in us. Having done all for us in a way of Purchaſe and Merit, and all in us in a way of ſoveraign Grace and Almighty Power; owning and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever Grace there is already in our hearts, we had it from his fulneſs in whom it pleaſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that all fulneſs ſhould dwell. And what farther ſupplys of Grace we ſhall ſtand in need of, we muſt ſtill have it from him who is not only the head of Government to his Church, but the head of Influence too, in whom dwelleth all the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Godhead bodily. A ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of wiſdom as the Prophet of the Church. A fulneſs of Merit as the Prieſt of the Church. A fulneſs of Power and Efficacy as the King of the Church. A fulneſs of all habit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual created Grace, not for himſelf only, but in a way of Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Derivation to others, the Godhead continually emptying it ſelf into the Manhood by vertue of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35041:26"/>that near cloſe, intimous union of the Humane with the Divine Nature in the Perſon of Chriſt: from this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is that we are ſtill expecting freſh ſupplies of Grace and Comfort. Diſtruſting our own ſtrength as well as renouncing our own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſubmitting to all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and ordinances of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. A proud heart ſhakes off the Yoke of Chriſt, and will not be ſubject to the Lord the Redeemer, and will be under the government of none but his own will, and his own luſts, like thoſe proud Citizens we read of in <hi>Luke,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>We will not have this man to reign over us.</hi> We walk humbly when we lie at Chriſt's foot, deſiring to know his pleaſure, claiming no power over our ſelves, or any thing that we have, but intirely ſubmit our ſelves to be commanded and governed by him, ſubmiting our ſelves wholly to his command and conduct. This is to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35041:27"/>walk humbly, and thus we are to walk after this Supper.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. More Thankfully. What Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for us, calls for the higheſt and moſt raiſed Thankſgivings from us. We are to ſcrew our Praiſes to the higheſt note. Let us ſay to our Souls as holy <hi>David</hi> did to his, <hi>Bleſs the Lord O our ſouls, and let all that is within us bleſs his holy Name;</hi> for his redeeming love, who loved us and gave himſelf for us, an Offering and a Sacrifice to ſatisfie Divine Juſtice. O how ſhould we be ſinging that new ſong of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above, ſaying, <hi>Thou art worthy to take the book, and to open the ſeals thereof, for thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us unto God by thine own Blood, out of every Kindred and Tongue and People and Nation, and haſt made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts, and we ſhall reign on the earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive Power and Riches,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35041:27"/>and Wiſdom and Strength, and Honour and Glory and Bleſſing.</hi> The work that Chriſt came to do and finiſh for us had in it all the expreſſions of love, and calls for the greateſt expreſſions of thankfulneſs and praiſe. This is a juſt debt that we owe to Chriſt. All the evil and miſery we are freed and delivered from, and the good we are poſſeſſed and made partakers of, is owing to the Obedience and Sufferings of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Now that our hearts may be the more affected with this love of Chriſt, and drawn out in thankfulneſs to him, let us conſider the evils we are delivered from, and the good we are poſſeſſed and made partakers of by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First.</hi> The evils and miſeries we are delivered from, and they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great indeed. But what are they you will ask? why the guilt of ſin, the curſe of the Law, the wrath of God, and the flames of Hell. Man's
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35041:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtate was once an holy ſtate, and, whilſt ſuch, an holy ſtate. But it was not long that he continued in this ſtate, being left to the freedom of his own will, he quickly fell from that ſtate in which he was created, by ſinning againſt God, which ſin was the Inlet of all miſery. It wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully corrupted, depraved, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed our Natures, robbed us of the Image of God, which once was the greateſt ornament and perfection of our Nature, deprived us of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Fellowſhip and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, laid us open and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to his wrath and curſe, to all the miſeries of this Life, and to the pains of Hell for ever. O the depth of miſery that all Mankind is plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into! O the innumerable evils that do encompaſs and ſurround us! Temporal, Spititual, and, if not found in Chriſt, Eternal evils too will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us; but in and through Chriſt Believers are delivered from all that evil and miſery that the Fall and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35041:28"/>of our Firſt Parents involved all. Mankind into. Through him the Guilt of Sin is removed, the Wrath and Anger of God appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the Thundering Law ſilenced, the Image of God reſtored, many Powerful and Potent Enemies Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and Subdued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly.</hi> The good which we are poſſeſſed and made partakers of, this alſo is owing to Chriſt, to what he hath done and ſuffered for us, even the good of preſent Grace, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Glory; the good of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sanctification, Reconciliation, for all theſe great benefits and good things we are beholden to Chriſt. We are Juſtified by his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Sanctified by his Spirit, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled by his Attoning Blood, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted by virtue of our Union with him, and relation to Chriſt's Perſon, as he is God's Natural Son. All theſe bleſſed Benefits and Priviledges that we are made partakers of, are
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35041:29"/>owing unto Chriſt. As the evils we lay under were too great for any meer creature to remove; ſo the good things we ſtand in need of, are too great for any mere creature to procure. None beſide that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who was God as well as Man, could either remove the one or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the other. Had not Chriſt himſelf undertaken the work no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could have been done; had not this Samaritain taken pitty and compaſſion on us in our miſerable and forlorn condition we muſt for ever have diſpaired of mercy or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. The Lord looked and there was none to help, at length his own arm brought Salvation. As for us we lay under an eternal incapacity, and impoſſibility of helping or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving our ſelves; as for Angels they could not help us, could any creature have done the work God would have employed that creature and ſpared his own Son. But God very well knew that Redemption work
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35041:29"/>was no work for an Angel, no not for the whole Body of Angels. If the whole order of them had come from Heaven, and united all their force and ſtrength together they could not have redeemed ſo much as one Soul. How far God by his Almighty power could have enabled an Angel to have born up under the greateſt ſufferings we will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, but ſuppoſe an Angel might have been furniſhed with ſo much ſtrength as to have been able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo and ſuffer all that Chriſt did, yet under the higheſt communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of grace and ſtrength to him, he being ſtill but a meer finite Creature, could never ſatisfie for what was paſt, nor Merit for what was to come; he could neither expiate Sin, nor procure Eternal Life. No, theſe are things which could only be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed and brought about by him who was more than a meer finite or Created Being, even by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35041:30"/>Man but God too: you ſee then we are beholden to Chriſt for all. He it is that fetcheth ſinners from the loweſt Hell, and lodgeth them in the higheſt Heavens, that ſnatcheth them from the deepeſt Miſery, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth them to the higheſt Glory that poor finite beings are capable of. O the great obligations that are upon us to walk thankfully all our days. Every time we partake of this Supper-Ordinance, we come under new and freſh obligations of thankfulneſs. We that have been ſo lately feaſting upon his love, ſo lately put in mind of the great things he hath been doing for us, before whoſe eyes Jeſus Chriſt in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt expreſſions of his love hath been evidently ſet forth and Crucified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and the bleſſed benefits of his Death and Crucifixion repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, ſealed and applied to us. Our Bleſſed Lord would not have his love in doing and Suffering for us be forgotten by us, and therefore hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35041:30"/>appointed this Supper as a ſtanding monument and memorial thereof to his Church. When we eat the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Bread and drink the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Cup, we are to do it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him, of what he hath done and ſuffered for us. This was a kindneſs never to be forgotten, at the Inſtitution of which Supper we find he himſelf gave thanks, <note n="*">
                        <hi>Rob.</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, <hi>page 178.</hi>
                     </note> 1 Cor. 11.23.24. <hi>For I have received of the Lord, that which alſo I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jeſus the ſame night in which he was betrayed took bread, and when he had given thanks he break it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>after the ſame manner alſo he took the cup.</hi> Now what was the matter or form of this thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving is not expreſſed, but it is moſt likely it was in reference to the work or action then in hand, and not only for the bare outward Elements, but more cheifly and eſpecially for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Myſterys and excellent benefits to be repreſented and ſealed by them.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35041:31"/>For the Grace and love of God which he came to diſcover to Mankind, and was now about to ſeal with his own Blood. The Baptiſm he was to be baptiſed with was now approaching, <hi>viz.</hi> his death, wherein his Body was to be broken, and his Blood ſhed for the life of the World, and for the nouriſhment of the Elect, which he delighted to accompliſh, or as he himſelf expreſſeth it, <hi>was ſtraitned till it was accompliſhed.</hi> Theſe were the things that were chiefly and ſpecially the matter of his thankſgiving. Now did Chriſt give thanks at the firſt Inſtitution? why then proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably we are ſtill to give thanks in all after Adminiſtrations of this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And not only juſt in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of it, but after we have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken we are to walk thankfully all the days of our lives, conſidering <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> The inward moving cauſe of all, which was the great love and mercy of God to us, John 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35041:31"/>only begotten Son.</hi> 1 John 4.10. <hi>Herein is love not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Son to be a propitiation for our ſins.</hi> Now this firſt inward moving cauſe of all, <hi>viz.</hi> the love of God, muſt not be overlooked, becauſe it is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, Rom. 5.8. <hi>But God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth his love to us in that white we were yet ſinners Chriſt died for us.</hi> Some things are barely related to us but this is commended to us, that we may be ſure never to forget it, and to be continual matter of praiſe and thankſgiving to us; conſidering (2.) The outward occaſion or procuring cauſe, which is Mans miſery by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſin. This was the outward occaſion of Chriſt's coming into the World, and doing what he did, and ſuffering what he ſuffered. He came to reconcile and propitiate God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Mans ſin. To remove that enmity that was betwixt God and us, to appeaſe the anger and wrath of God towards us; now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35041:32"/>this can be brought about and effected the Son of God muſt become Man, obey and ſuffer, bleed and dye to expiate our offences. And doth not this afford us continual matter of thankſgiving. Once more, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect and fruit and benefit of all that he hath done and ſuffered for us, and that is life, that whether we wake or ſleep we ſhould live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him. This was the white that Chriſt aimed at in all that he did; next to his Fathers glory was the ſalvation and life of poor ſinners, that we might live, how? why a life of pardon and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in Juſtification, a life of grace and holineſs in Sanctification, a life of joy and peace in Conſolation, and a life of bliſs and happineſs in Glorification. Theſe are things that our thoughts ſhould be much em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about and affected with at the Table, and ſhall we not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward look upon our ſelves as laid under the higheſt obligations of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35041:32"/>thankfulneſs, of walking thankfully all our days. We never have been ſo much beholden to any perſon, but we are infinitely more beholden to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, therefore the whole of our lives ſhould be nothing elſe but continual expreſſions of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to Chriſt. But here it may be asked how ſhould we expreſs our thankfulneſs?</p>
                  <p>To this I Anſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By often thinking of it our ſelves, and ſpeaking of it to others to his glory. We are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs to Chriſt for what he hath done, by giving and aſcribing all the Glory to him, attributing and aſcribing nothing to our ſelves, but all to the riches of his Grace, and freeneſs of his Love. To look upon our ſelves as any ways deſerving what he hath done for us, doth greatly detract from his Glory, and argues a baſe diſingenuous ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35041:33"/>temper to be in us. Alas, Who are we, or what are we, poor worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs worms, not worthy that he ſhould ſpend a thought upon us, and much leſs that he ſhould lay down his Life, and ſhed his Blood for us? Pray let us a little reflect, and conſider what we were not long ago; Dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, wallowing in the filth and mire of Sin and Luſt, alienated from, nay enemies to God and Chriſt, poor, and miſerable, and blind, and naked, caſt out into the open Field, to the loathing of our perſons, polluted, and defiled in our Blood, not worth the taking notice of. Now than ever we ſhould be the Objects of his Love, who deſerved to be the Objects of his eternal diſdain, and the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Monuments of his Diſpleaſure. How ought this to be continually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by us to the Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace. This is one way by which we expreſs our Thankfulneſs for any kindneſs or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35041:33"/>favour receiv'd, when we think of it, or ſpeak of it, to the Praiſe and Renown of him that ſhewed it. So this is one way by which we are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for what he hath done and ſuffered for us, by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thinking of it our ſelves, or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to others, to the eternal praiſe and renown of our dear Redeemer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another way, by which we are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs, is by magnifying and ſetting an high eſteem and value upon what he hath done for us. Eſtimation of Benefits received is one way of expreſſing our Thankfulneſs for them. Unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs always leſſens, and vilifyes, and makes light of a kindneſs or benefit received, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did the <hi>Manna,</hi> Numb. 21.5. <hi>And the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpake againſt God, and againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Wherefore have you brought us up out of Aegypt to dye in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? for there is no bread, neither is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35041:34"/>there any water, and our ſoul loatheth this light bread,</hi> Numb. 11.5.6. <hi>We remember the fiſh we did freely eat in Aegypt, the Cucumbers and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, and the Leeks,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but now our ſoul is dried away, there is nothing at all beſides this Mannah before our eyes.</hi> Oh what unthankful, ungrateful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were theſe? to make light of ſuch excellent Food, which yeilded ſuch excellent nouriſhment, and in the ſtrength of which they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to go ſo many, and ſuch tedious Journeys. Their entertaining ſuch baſe, low, mean thoughts of it, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their great unthankfulneſs for it. Thus unthankful wretches do by Chriſt, even as theſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did by the <hi>Mannah,</hi> they make but light of Chriſt, the greateſt Gift that God could have beſtowed upon the Sons of Men. But yet at the ſame time, they deſpiſe both Giver and Gift it ſelf; by deſpiſing the Gift they affront the Giver. They ſee no lovelyneſs, no beauty, no excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35041:34"/>in Chriſt, that they ſhould deſire him. <hi>What is thy beloved more than another beloved,</hi> was the Anſwer to the Spouſe, when ſhe was ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly enquiring after her Beloved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. A Luſt, a Pleaſure, is by many preferred before Chriſt. A Luſt that will Damn them, before a Saviour that will Save them. A Carnal Pleaſure ſhall be embraced, when Chriſt and his Benefits ſhall be deſpiſed, this argues great Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and Unthankfulneſs, vilifies and leſſens both the Perſon that ſhews the kindneſs, and the kindneſs it ſelf; when as true Thankfulneſs eſteems and values both Perſon and Benefit; both he that hath done, and what he hath done for us. Now this way we are to expreſs our Thanfulneſs to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of him, and the Benefits we receive by him. Now what eſteem have we for Chriſt? Do we eſteem him as the Apoſtle did, who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and determined to know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35041:35"/>elſe but Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. He looked upon all other knowledge as vain and unprofitable in compariſon of Chriſt and him Crucifyed; this ſhewed his value and eſteem for Chriſt. And ſuch an eſteem had he for Chriſt, that he counted all things but loſs for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt; yea, all things but dung that he might win Chriſt, and be ſound in him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8, 9. He could deſpiſe and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon the pleaſures and profits and preferments of this preſent World, that he might but win Chriſt and be found in him. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and undergo the greateſt hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and ſufferings for the Name and ſake of Chriſt. The greateſt of his glorying and boaſting was in a Crucifyed Jeſus; <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the Croſs of Jeſus Christ, by which the world is crucifyed unto me, and I unto the world.</hi> Nothing had that place in his eſteem as Chriſt's had. And
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35041:35"/>then is our eſteem of Chriſt right indeed, when we eſteem him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, and before all; above Eſtate, above Relations, above all other outward comforts and conveniencies, when we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to let go all for Chriſt. I am ſure there is that worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in Chriſt, both Perſonal and Relative, whether we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him as he is in himſelf, or in thoſe comfortable relations he ſtands in to his People; I ſay, conſider him which way we will, in his Offices, in his Grace and Fullneſs, in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Glorious Titles, and there is that in Chriſt, which truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves our greateſt and higheſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem. Thus we are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs by our high Eſteem of Chriſt of his Perſon, and as of his Perſon, ſo of his Deeds and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of what he hath done and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us, and the great Benefits that iſſue and proceed from thence. Is it not wonderful, that a Perſon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35041:36"/>ſo high and honourable, ſo excellent and glorious, that the Son of God, and God by Nature, who was equal with God in Glory, Wiſdom and Power, and in all other Divine Excellencies and Perfections, that he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this Glory of his to lie obſcure for a time, under the Vail of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature? That a Perſon ſo far above and beyond us ſhould come and joyn himſelf to us, Marry into ſuch a poor broken beggarly Family as ours? That he who was Lord of the Law, ſhould be made under the Law, under the Obſervation of the Law, to fulfil the Righteouſneſs thereof; and under the Malediction of the Law, to undergo the Penalty and Curſe of it? That the Judge of Quick and Dead ſhould become Undertaker for Guilty Condemned Wretches? That he who knew no ſin, ſhould be made ſin, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to be dealt with as if he had been the Chiefe of Sinners, bruiſed and broken upon the Wheel of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35041:36"/>Wrath, Reproached and Vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by Men, forſaken of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>vir dolorum,</hi> a Man of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and acquainted with Grief? O the pains of Body, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of Spirit that he underwent, the wearyſome Life, and at laſt the Painful and Accurſed Death that he endured, and all this to ſave an handful, that were not worth the looking after, or taking notice of, who neither deſired it, nor deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it. Well might it be ſaid, <hi>That he had mercy upon whom he will have mercy;</hi> and that he loved us becauſe he loved us. Alas! Who are we, or what are we, that Chriſt ſhould fix his heart's Love upon us? Would we know what we were? why loſt undone miſerable Sinners, Enemies, nay Enmity it ſelf, dead in Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Sin, in the Gall of Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Bond of Iniquity. Many of them, for whom Chriſt hath done and ſuffer'd ſuch things, were, it may be, Blaſphemers, Perſecutors,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35041:37"/>and Injurious to Chriſt and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. Such an one was that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Servant of Chriſt the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as he himſelf acknowledges, 1 Tim. 1.12.13. <hi>And I thank Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful, putting me into the Ministry, who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Blaſphemer, and a Perſecuter, and Injurious, but I obtained mercy,</hi> &amp;c. Some of them, it may be, have been guilty of the fouleſt and groſſeſt Sins, as ſome of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> were, <hi>Fornicators, Idolaters, Adulterérs, Thieves, Drunkards,</hi> &amp;c.yet theſe obtained Mercy, were Waſhed, were Sanctifyed, were Juſtifyed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God, as we read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 11. Even then when there was nothing but unworthyneſs and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minableneſs in us, did Chriſt-dye for us. Now is this a thing to be made light of? or to be lightly eſteemed of by us? this argues us to be the moſt ungrateful, unthankful wretches
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35041:37"/>living upon the Face of the Earth. The very Angels ſtand and wonder, and vent their aſtoniſhment at what Chriſt hath done for us; And ſhall not we admire at it our ſelves? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there ſuch love manifeſted before nor ſince. <hi>Greater love than this hath no Man, than that a Man lay down his life for his friends,</hi> John 15.13. But Chriſt hath evidenced greater than this, in doing and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and laying down his Life for his Enemies Hereby perceive we the love of God, becauſe he laid down his Life for us; What for us Friends? no: but for us Enemies, Rom. 5.10. nay for us Enmity it ſelf, Rom. 8.7. <hi>The carnal mind is enmity againſt God.</hi> Was ever love like this love? The Apoſtle Prays for the <hi>Epheſians, That they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth and length, and depth, and heighth, and to know the love of Christ which paſſeth knowledge,</hi> Eph. 3.18, 19. Here are Four Dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35041:38"/>that the Apoſtle meaſures this love of Chriſt by; <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> knows but Three, viz. <hi>Longitudo, Latitudo, &amp; Profunditas.</hi> Length, Breadth, and Depth. But <hi>Divinity</hi> adds a Fourth, <hi>viz. Altitudo,</hi> Height. To intimate, that Chriſt's Love is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all ordinary Meaſure and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions. There is Depth in it, ſays <note n="†">
                        <hi>Roberts</hi> Communicant, <hi>p. 186.</hi>
                     </note> one, without bottom. There is Height in it without top, Breadth in it without ſide, and Length in it without end. Yea, it infinitely ſurpaſſeth the capacity and graſp of a finite limited underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to comprehend and take in. And O that every one of us who have been ſo lately Celebrating and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorating the Death and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our Loving Lord, that have had ſuch Lively Repreſentations of what he hath been doing and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for us, may find our eſteem in ſome meaſure and degree anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and proportionable to the love
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35041:38"/>that was manifeſted and evidenced in it.</p>
                  <p>But yet farther there is another conſideration in what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered which if rightly and duely weighed, might be a means of raiſing and heightning our eſteem of it, and that is the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, efficacy, acceptableneſs and merit of his Obedience and Sufferings. This was an odour of a ſweet ſmell, moſt acceptable to God. The Law was fully anſwered, and Divine Juſtice was fully ſatisfied in their fulleſt and higheſt demands. Tho' his Sufferings were but ſhort, yet what was wanting in the duration of them was infinitely and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made up in the dignity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Perſon that ſuffered, for it was infinitely more that the Son of God ſhould ſuffer one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than if all the Angels in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Men upon Earth had ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Eternity. Such a ſufficiency there is in what Chriſt hath done
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35041:39"/>and ſuffered, that there needs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to be done, nothing more to be ſuffered in a way of ſatisfaction to the Juſtice of God, for he by once offering up of himſelf hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified, Heb. 10.14. <hi>There needs no more ſacrifice for ſin.</hi> There is ſufficiency enough in the Death and Blood of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to procure pardon for the greateſt of ſins and the chiefeſt of ſinners, to redeem and ſave the whole World, nay ten thouſand Worlds. And if it ſhould be asked why are not then all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and ſaved? To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it is not upon the account of any inſufficiency of the Blood of Chriſt, for it is ſufficient to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed as many Worlds as there be Stars in the Firmament; it was ſufficient to have redeemed all, but it was not ſhed for all, but only thoſe that the Father from all Eternity gave to him. For theſe and theſe only it was ſhed, to theſe and theſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35041:39"/>only it becomes effectual unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Salvation. It pleaſed the Father from all Eternity to elect ſome to everlaſting life, theſe in the Covenant of Redemption he gave to Chriſt to redeem and ſave, theſe Chriſt undertook and engaged for in that ſame Covenant tranſaction, for theſe he dyed and ſuffered, and ſhed his hearts Blood, which was a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient price for their redemption, it being the blood of that Perſon who was God as well as Man. The dignity of the Perſon was that which highly dignified his Paſſion. This was that which put ſuch an All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency into the Death and Blood of Chriſt, that made it ſufficient for all the ends for which it was deſigned. O that poor trembling ſouls and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving hearts would conſider of this and take hold of it, and plead it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the accuſations of the Law, againſt all the accuſations of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, againſt all the ſubtile charges of the Devil. Poor Soul, it may be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35041:40"/>thou art terrified and amazed at the ſight and ſenſe of thy ſinfulneſs and guiltineſs, it may be many doubts and fears and ſcruples are ready to ariſe in thy mind whether ever God will look upon, or accept of, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into favour ſuch an one as thou art, but know this for thy comfort whoever thou art, that there cannot be ſo much Unrighteouſneſs in thee to render thee loathſome, but there is more Righteouſneſs in Chriſt to render thee lovely in the ſight of God. There is ſufficiency enough in what Chriſt hath done and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to procure God's favour and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, only do thou ſtedfaſtly rely upon it, and put thy whole truſt in it; never did any miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry who ventured their all upon this bottom. There is ſufficiency enough in the Blood of Chriſt to procure pardon for as many ſins as there are moments in thy Life, or thoughts in thy heart. Be thy ſins never ſo many for multitude, or never ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35041:40"/>great for aggravation, yet the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth from all Unrighteouſneſs. Not only from leſſer, but from greater Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; not only from ſome, but from all Unrighteouſneſs. Tho it is true, there is one ſin which is called a ſin unto Death, or the unpardonable ſin, which ſhall never be forgiven, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Life nor that which is to come, and that is the ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> But it is not upon the account of any inſufficiency in the Blood of Chriſt that this ſin is Unpardonable; but he that ſins this ſin is rendered altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of laying hold of, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Remedy, <hi>viz.</hi> the Blood of Chriſt, which, in it ſelf, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to cleanſe from all Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>The laſt conſideration is the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Benefits that do iſſue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from hence, and ſo we are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs by an high eſteem of them. Hereby ſinners are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35041:41"/>Juſtified and ſin purged away, the guilt of ſin that was ſo wounding to the Conſcience is removed. Hereby enemies to God are reconciled, and peace with God procured, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, nay the enmity is removed, and God and the Soul walk together, as thoſe that be well agreed. God and the Soul holding a moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful converſe with each other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there was a ſhineſs before, now there is acceſs with the greateſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and boldneſs. Hereby Death, and he that had the power of Death, that is the Devil, with all Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and Powers are ſubdued, the Kingdom and Intereſt of Sin and Satan overthrown in the Soul, and freedom from ſpiritual thraul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is obtained; The Son having made us free we are become free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Theſe are great priviledges, and O that our eſteem of them were ſome way anſwerable to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them. Tho' we come eaſily by them, yet they coſt Chriſt dear
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35041:41"/>to purchaſe. He was at a greater expenſe to Redeem one Soul than he was to create a whole World, the one was done by the word of his Power, he ſpake and it was done, but the other is done by the blood of his heart, and he muſt dye before it be done. His life muſt be laid down, a life more worth than all the lives of Men upon Earth, or Angels in Heaven. They came freely unto us, but he muſt dye and ſuffer to purchaſe and procure them. O that our Souls may with <hi>Mary</hi> magnifie the Lord who hath regarded the low eſtate of his ſervants, for he that is mighty hath done great things for us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="particular">
                  <p>3. Another way by which we are to expreſs our Thankfulneſs, is by rendering again according to the Benefits we have received. But when F ſpeak of rendering back again ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the benefit received, I do not mean in a way of recompenſe, but in token of our Thankfulneſs.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35041:42"/>Alas we are in no capacity of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing or making him amends for his kindneſs to us, his love in doing and dying for us infinitely exceeds all our returns. There is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt the light and heat of a Spark to the light and heat of the Sun, than there is between his kindneſs and our returns. When we have done all we can, and ſuffered all we can for him it is nothing to what he hath done and ſuffered for us. But tho' we cannot make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable returns, yet we are to make ſuteable and becoming returns for the Mercys and Benefits we have received from him. It is ſaid in 2 Chron. 32.25. <hi>That Hezekiah render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not according to the benefit he had received.</hi> That is, he did not make ſuteable and becoming returns for the great benefits he had received, <hi>viz.</hi> that wonderful Victory he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained over the <hi>Aſſirian</hi> Army men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> And that miraculous reſtoration and recovery
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35041:42"/>from a very dangerous illneſs, and the confirmation of that work by a ſtrange and ſupernatural motion of the Sun. All which inſtead of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him low and humble, probably raiſed him up to an high conceit and opinion of himſelf, as if theſe great things had been done, if not by his own power, yet at leaſt for his Piety and goodneſs. And inſtead of walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humbly with his God, and giving the glory of all intirely and wholly to God, he took the honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and vainly ſhewed his Riches and precious Treaſures to the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> Ambaſſadors. Now this was not a return any way ſuteable or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the great benefits he had ſo lately received. So that I ſay tho' we cannot make proportionable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, yet we muſt look to it that we make ſuteable returns to our loving Jeſus for the great and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful benefits we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of in and thro' him. That as his heart was enlarged in love and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35041:43"/>pity and conpaſſion towards us, ſo our hearts ſhould be enlarged in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to him. We ſhould be putting that queſtion to our own Souls which holy <hi>David</hi> did to his, Pſal. 116.12. <hi>What ſhall we render unto the Lord for all his benefits towards us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here it may be asked what is it that we ought to render unto the Lord Jeſus for thoſe expreſſions of his love in doing and ſuffering for us, and for all the great and bleſſed benefits that do flow and proceed from hence?</p>
                  <p>To this I Anſwer. We muſt and ought to render our whole ſelves to him, Rom. 12.1. <hi>I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Brethren by the mercys of God that ye preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, Holy, acceptable unto God which is your reaſonable ſervice.</hi> Here is an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the motive or argument by which he doth urge it. The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and that is, to preſent our Bodies a living Sacrifice Holy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God; or to give, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35041:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>devote, or offer up our whole ſelves, Souls and Bodies, unto God. It is true, the Body is only mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Soul muſt not be exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is a Synechdochical expreſſion where a part is put for the whole. That then which we are to render unto Chriſt in token of our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and gratitude, is our whole ſelves, Souls and Bodies, all that we are and have, to live to him, to ſuffer for him, when ever he ſhall call us out thereto, to be ſaved by him, and not only ſo, but to be ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by him. Submitting our ſelves to the conduct of his wife Providence and to the laws and rules of his moſt Spiritual Government: That is to ſay, when no Luſt or Corruption bears Rule or Sway in our hearts, but when every thing within us, and every thing without us is captivated and brought over to the obedience to the Lord Jeſus. When Chriſt, by his Spirit, makes entrance into our hearts, and takes full poſſeſſion of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35041:44"/>all the powers and faculties of our Souls, and of all the members of our Bodies, that whereas they have once been ſtrongly and deeply engaged in the ways and ſervice of Sin, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come now as deeply and ſtrongly engaged for Chriſt, and in his ways and Service. As when we ſee a Perſon in the full height and carreer of ſin, proſecuting with all his might his carnal corrupted deſires and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, at the beck and command of that corrupt Principle that is within him, employing that Reaſon and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtauding, and Parts which God hath endowed him with, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of any ſinful thing or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his power and ſtrength, for the perfecting and accompliſhing, and obtaining what he had ſo contrived and plotted; why ſuch a Perſon may be ſaid to be given up to his Luſts and Corruptions, but not to Chriſt. So on the other hand, where we ſee a Perſon at the beck and command of Chriſt, employing his Reaſon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35041:44"/>and Underſtanding, his Strength and Parts for the Honour and Glory of Chriſt, obedient to, and complying with every call and command of Chriſt, induſtriouſly proſecuting the Glory of Chriſt, as the great end of Life, heartily ſubmitting to his Laws and Commands, as the great and only Rule of Life; why ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may truly be ſaid to be given up to Chriſt. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. ſpeaks there of Perſons that had given up themſelves to Chriſt, and ſpeaks it in praiſe of the <hi>Macedonians.</hi> This they did, ſays he; Why what did they do? why they did liberally and bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Communicate to the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Poor Saints at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> they did to their Power, nay, they did beyond their Power, their Charity was larger than their Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; thus open-handed, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted were theſe <hi>Macedonians.</hi> Where ſhall we find ſuch Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Profeſſours in our days? Well
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35041:45"/>then, this they did; And was this all that they did? No: they did not only give the greateſt parts of their Eſtates towards the Relief of the poor diſtreſſed Saints, but they gave their own ſelves unto the Lord. This they did, not as we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that is, <note n="*">Eraſm.</note> 
                     <hi>Multo amplius quam ſper are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debamus;</hi> much more than we could hope; they exceeded our hopes and expectations. But wherein? why, <hi>Quia non ſuas tantum facultates habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt expoſitas, ſed ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos impendere parati fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt,</hi> 
                     <note n="†">Calvin.</note> ſayes one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were ready not only to beſtow their Goods, but to offer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo themſelves. They gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſayes he, firſt to the Lord, and then to us by the will of God. The giving of their Eſtates towards the relief of the Saints, was highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in them. Their relieving others was very well, eſpecially when they were ſo low themſelves. But
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35041:45"/>this was not all, there was ſtill ſome thing higher than this, they gave themſelves to the Lord. To give their Eſtates was vety much, but to give themſelves was much more, and this was that which was given by theſe Believers. <hi>Non ſolum res ſuas ſed ſemetipſos dederunt domino quaſi ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium immaculatum</hi> 
                     <note n="*">Anſelm.</note>. They did not only give their Subſtance, but Themſelves unto the Lord, as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted, undefiled Sacrifice: Now to this great work and buſineſs of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up our ſelves to the Lord, I would hope there be none of us ſtrangers to it, who have, this day, been ſitting down at our Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I would hope that this hath been, in ſome meaſure, done by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us, before we did firſt venture to ſit down at this Table. Elſe from the time we firſt ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon this Ordinance, we have been eating and drinking Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our ſelves. All that draw
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35041:46"/>nigh to this Table, who have not firſt given themſelves to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, are unfit and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gueſts indeed. We find that theſe <hi>Macedonians,</hi> firſt gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto the Lord, before they ſat down in Church-fellowſhip and Communion; They firſt gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto the Lord, and then to us by the will of God. They firſt joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves to the Lord, before they joyned in this great Ordinance of Communion. And this I have reaſon to hope concerning every one of you, that before you did venture upon this Solemn Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, that you were ſuch as had ſolemnly and ſeriouſly given up your ſelves to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But yet there are none of us ſo much given up to Chriſt, but we may be ſtill more given up to him. Alas, there is a great deal of Carnality, and Corruption, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helief, in the beſt and holyeſt on this ſide Heaven, which is the occaſion of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35041:46"/>frequent backſlidings, and Apoſtacys from God. And often times puts us upon doing thoſe things that are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much unbecoming the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelves to the Lord, too much harkening to the whiſperings of the Old Man. Too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with the Solicitations of the Fleſh. Top great an Adherence to the World, and Conformity to the Vanities and Pleaſures, to the Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries and Fopperies, and Faſhions, and Cuſtoms thereof. Too much Self-ſeeking, Self-love, and Self-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, all which are wonderful unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming this Serious and Solemn De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of our ſelves to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Therefore there is great need that this work be often and frequently renewed. It is not enough that it be done once, but it muſt be done often, and daily. It ought not to ſuffice us, that we be in ſome meaſure given up to Chriſt, but we muſt ſtill be more and more given up to him. Daily Backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35041:47"/>call for frequent and daily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newals of our Dedication. <hi>David</hi> renewed the Dedication of his Houſe after <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Sins, and alſo renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Dedication of his Perſon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own Foul and Perſonal Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages. Times of great Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on call for the Renewal of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. Thus when <hi>Jacob</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to great ſtraits, and knew not what to do, then he ſets upon the Renewing the Dedication of himſelf to God, <hi>If God,</hi> ſays he, <hi>will be with me in the way that I ſhall go, and will give me bread to eat, and rayment to put on,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then ſhall the Lord be my God,</hi> Gen. 28.20, 21. Again, renewed Mercys call for renewed dedication of our ſelves to God. And laſtly, great dutys call for this renewal of our dedication. Every time we Pray we are to renew our dedication. But in Sacramental work we muſt do it in a more ſolemn and explicit man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, not only before and at but after
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35041:47"/>that Ordinance, as coming under new and freſh Obligations and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to be the Lords. Thus much for the Exhortation, Preſent your Bodies a living Sacrifice holy acceptable to God, that is, give up your whole ſelves Souls and Bodies to the Lord. Now the Argument or motive by which he preſſeth it is the Mercies of God in that Rom. 12.1. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren by the Mercys of God that ye preſent your Bodies,</hi> &amp;c. The Mercys of God are a great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Motive to preſs us to this very thing, of giving up our ſelves to God. The Temporal, but eſpecially the Spiritual Mercys of God; he doth not ſay Mercy but Mercies, in the Plural number, becauſe they are many, <hi>viz.</hi> Election of Grace, Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt, Juſtification by Faith, Sanctification by the Spirit. By all theſe Mercies which are every one of them, more worth than a thouſand Worlds, he beſeecheth them to give up or preſent themſelves to God.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35041:48"/>As if an indulgent compaſſionate Mother ſhould beſeech her child to do ſomething, by the womb that bare him, by the paps that gave him ſuck, by the knees that dandled him, by the hands that fed him, by all her tender compaſſions and indulgence towards him. Certainly the heart of this child muſt be harder than any Flint, not to yeild to her, it would argue a temper very ungrateful not to comply with her. So it would argue our hearts very hard, and our tempers very ungrateful, not to yeild to God, when he that might condemn us doth intreat and beſeech, even by thoſe tender Mercies whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat us, pardoned us, called us, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and ſaved us. If Love and Kindneſs and Mercy will not win us and prevail upon us, pray what will? So the love of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his love in coming into the World, in aſſuming our Nature, his love in doing for us, and dying for us, and ſuffering for us is a great
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35041:48"/>Motive and Argument to perſwade us to give up our ſelves, and all that we are and have fully, and ſeriouſly and ſolemnly, to him in token of our gratitude and thankfulneſs. And O that the ſenſe and feeling and apprehenſion of this love of Chriſt, might conſtrain every ſoul of us to give up our ſelves to him. Are we bought with a Price? Are we Redeemed from the greateſt ſlavery and tyranny that ever poor creatures were under, from the Wrath and Vengeance of God who is a conſuming fire? From the Curſe and condemnation of the Law, from the dominion of Sin and Satan and the World? Why this is a great and unſpeakable Priviledge and happineſs indeed. Ay but how came we to be thus Redeemed? Why it was by a great price that was laid down and depoſited; <hi>ye are bought with a price,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. But what price was this? Was it Silver or Gold? no; it was by the price of Blood. But what
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35041:49"/>Blood was it? The Blood of Bulls and Goats? no; it was the Blood of the Son of God, 1 Pet. 1.18, 19. <hi>It was the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the eternal Son of God that redeemed us with his own Blood.</hi> What can we do leſs then glorifie him with our Bodies and Spirits. O how Thankfully ought we to walk all our days, and we cannot better expreſs our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs than by dedicating and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voting our ſelves to his ſervice and glory. This is the greateſt return that we can make and the higheſt gratitude. You know the firſt fruits were in former times dedicated unto God, partly to ſhow God's right to the whole crop, and partly in token of thankfulneſs from the people for all the reſt. Now this giving up our ſelves to the Lord Jeſus is the beſt expreſſion of our thankfulneſs that we can make. This exceeds the moſt melting acknowledgments, and the higheſt verbal reſentments of all his love and kindneſs to us. When a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35041:49"/>poor creature is deeply affected with a ſenſe of the love of Chriſt to him, falls down at the foot of Chriſt, and ſays Lord Jeſus I am one of thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones, whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed unto God by thine own moſt precious Blood, from the ſlavery and tyranny under which I lay, thou didſt freely lay down thy life to ſave mine, thou didſt ſhed thine own Blood, and offeredſt thy ſelf upon the Croſs a Sacrifice to ſatisfie Divine Juſtice, and make Attonement for my ſins, and to bring me nigh unto God who once was alienated from, and an enemy to Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, in my mind by wicked Works. And thou waſt not only offered upon the Croſs for me, but thou haſt been lately in the Supper Ordinance exhibited and offered to me with all the virtues, and benefits, and victories, and purchaſes, and priviledges of thy death, for the ſtrengthning and nouriſhing of my Faith, for the enlivening, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35041:50"/>and raiſing my hope, for the filling up my joy and encreaſing my comfort, for the carrying on the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life with greater vigour and power in my Soul, for all this dear Jeſus, how ſhall I expreſs and teſtifie my Thankfulneſs? Why I will do it thus, I do here ſolemnly and ſeriouſly and fully give up my ſelf to thee to be thine and only thine both now and to Eternity, that is to ſay everlaſtingly thine. This is the beſt way of expreſſing our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and this we are every one afreſh obliged to, who have been ſitting down this day at our Lords Table. For one end of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is to be a ſeal of the Covenant, all the Bleſſings and Benefits and Priviledges and Promiſes and Grace of the New Covenant are confirmed to Believers by it. Now the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant binds mutually, God bindeth himſelf to give Grace to us, and we bind our ſelves to live to him. In all Covenants there is not only ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35041:50"/>to be done for us, but there is ſomething to be performed by us, God ſeals the Benefits of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant on his part, and we ſeal to the Durys of the Covenant on our part. The exhibiting the ſignes is the ſeal on God's part, the receiving the ſignes is the ſeal on our part. Every time we receive, we bind our ſelves to new and better Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to live more to God, and to dy more to ſin. I have Read, that <hi>Pliny</hi> ſhould ſay, (he learned it of ſome Chriſtians) That, at their Meeting, they did <hi>Sacramento ſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringere, ne furta, ne latrocinia, ne adulteria committerent,</hi> &amp;c. Bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Sacrament, that they would not commit theſe ſins of Theft, and Robbery, and Adultery. And ſo ſhould every one that have been eating the Sacramental Bread and Wine, look upon our ſelves as bound to live more to God and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to cleave to the Lord with fuller purpoſes of heart, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35041:51"/>more ſtedfaſt Reſolutions of Soul. Our Bleſſed Saviour never Inſtituted this Holy Ordinance to qualify Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for ſome advantagious Poſt, and to ſit Men for Publick Places and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or to be a Stepping-ſtone to Worldly Preferment, as it is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days only uſed by many, to the great ſhame of a Proteſtant Nation may it be ſpoken, that ſo Sacred an Ordinance ſhould be thus Abuſed and Prophaned. But he deſigned it to be a ſtronger Tye and Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon us, to a more Holy Life and Circumſpect Walk; and indeed if we do not anſwer this end, we do but Prophane this Ordinance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very time we partake of it. And inſtead of eating and drinking to our own Salvation, we ſhall but eat and drink Damnation to our ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="particular">
                  <p n="4">4. We are to Walk after this Ordinance more Believingly and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducially; that is, with a ſtronger Faith, and Truſt in Chriſt, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35041:51"/>upon him, 2 Col. 6. <hi>As ye have therefore received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him, rooted and built up in him, and ſtabliſht in the Faith, as you have been taught, abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein with Thankſgiving.</hi> None are ſo ſtabliſhed but they may grow ſtill in Faith. None have taken ſo much root, but they may take yet more root. Faith is ſuch a Grace as is capable of farther improvement. A weak Faith may become ſtrong, and a ſtrong Faith may become yet ſtronger. The Apoſtles prayer was this, <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith,</hi> Luke 17.9. Many are crying out for more Riches, for more Honour, for more Wealth, for more Pleaſure. But let this be the deſire of our Souls for a ſtronger Faith. This is a Petition very proper and ſuteable to be put up by us after we have been at this Supper, <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith.</hi> What the Apoſtle ſaid of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> concerning Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love, <hi>You need not that I
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35041:52"/>write unto you, for you your ſelves are taught of God to love one another, and indeed you do it towards all the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which are in all Macedonia.</hi> But yet he ſaw it neceſſary to preſs after a farther growth, and encreaſe of it. <hi>But we beſeech brethren, that ye encreaſe more and more.</hi> The ſame I truſt may be ſaid of many here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Faith. Ye are taught of God to believe, and indeed ye do believe; but however this Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or deſire is not needleſs, <hi>viz. That ye encreaſe more and more.</hi> Thoſe that have any meaſure of Faith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, are to be endeavouring after a growth and encreaſe in it. For the ſtronger our Faith is, the greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of Glory we bring to Chriſt. It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham, He was ſtrong in Faith, giving Glory to God,</hi> Rom. 4.20. But how did he glorify God? why, by believing in hope againſt hope. He glorifyed the Faithfulneſs and Truth, and the Power of God, that notwithſtanding the outward
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35041:52"/>Diſcouragement, under which he lay, tho' it ſeemed to be a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely improbable thing to the eye of Senſe and Reaſon that he ſhould have a Child, conſidering his own Age, and the Deadneſs of <hi>Sarahs</hi> Womb, yet he believed in the Power and Faithfulneſs of God, that he was able to performe what he promiſed to him, and that he would be true and faithful to perform it. Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> by his Faith, Glorifyed God's Power, Truth and Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And thus by believing we bring a great Revenue of Honour and Glory unto Chriſt. When we ſtedfaſtly rely upon the Merit and All-ſufficiency of his Blood for the Pardon of all our Sins, and under the freſh guilt we are contracting daily; we daily apply and betake our ſelves to this Blood of Chriſt for freſh Pardon and Cleanſing, when we ſtedfaſtly rely upon his Righteouſneſs for our Juſtifycation before God; not mentioning a word
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35041:53"/>of our own Inherent Righteouſneſs or Holineſs for our Juſtification and Acceptance with God, but make mention of his and of his only, when under all our Temptations we rely upon his Mercy and Faithfulneſs to help and ſuccour us. In all our ways to rely upon his Wiſdom for our guidance and conduct; when in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very act and duty of Worſhip we rely upon him for our acceſs to God. We never bring more honour and glory unto Chriſt than when we go moſt out of our ſelves, and rely moſt upon Chriſt. This is to walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievingly, and thus we are to walk after this Supper, <hi>viz.</hi> with a ſtronger Faith and truſt on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. We walk by Faith ſays the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. And in another place, <hi>The life which I now live in the Fleſh, I live by faith in the Son of God.</hi> Gal. 2.20. And thus we are to live and walk, <hi>viz.</hi> with a ſtronger Faith, with a more ſtedfaſt truſt and reliance upon Chriſt, upon his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35041:53"/>and Satisfaction. To this end was he lifted up upon the Croſs, and offered there, <hi>viz.</hi> to be believed in and reſted upon, Joh. 3.14, 15. <hi>As Moſes lifted up the Serpent in the wilderneſs, even ſo muſt the ſon of man be lifted up that whoſoever believeth in him,</hi> &amp;c. To this end did God the Father give Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to be believed in and reſted upon, verſ. 16 <hi>For God ſo loved the world that be gave his only begotten Son that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh,</hi> &amp;c. To this end is he lifted up in the preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> that poor ſinners might believe on, and put all their truſt and confidence in him for life and for Salvation. Mark 16.15, 16. <hi>Go into all the World and preach the Goſpel to every Creature, he that believeth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And to this end is he offered to us in the Supper, <hi>viz.</hi> to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in and reſted upon, 1 Cor. 11.23, 24, 25. <hi>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt the ſame night in which he was betrayed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35041:54"/>took Bread, and when he had given thanks brake it, and ſaid, take eat, this is my body which is broken for you. After the ſame manner he took the Cup when he had ſupped, ſaying, this Cup is the New Teſtament of my blood this do ye as often as ye drink it in remembrance of me,</hi> And in another place, <hi>drink ye all of it, this do in remembrance of me.</hi> In the Bread broken upon the Table we have a lively repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt's broken Body. In the Wine we have a lively repreſentation of the Blood of the Lord Jeſus the price of our Redemption. By Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand believing, ſo that we ſee the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ered to us in this Supper to be believed in and reſted upon. It is true, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but bare Bread and Wine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it ſelf to the eye of our Bodies; But under theſe outward Signes and Elements of Bread and Wine, there is a broken Crucified Saviour offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and preſented to the eye of our
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35041:54"/>Faith. O there is great need' of Faith and great work for Faith in our receiving and after our receiving, in our partaking and after we have partaken of this Supper, whilſt we ſit down and after we are riſen up from this Table.</p>
                  <p>There is great need of Faith and great work for Faith in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving. We can no more turn Bread and Wine into the Body and Blood of Chriſt without faith, ſays one, than a Chymiſt can tranſmute one Metal into another without the operation of the fire. He that comes to this Supper without faith, ſays another, is like a Man that thinks to quench his thirſt by ſucking the Ale bowl. Alas what is it that we receive at this Supper? why it is but a little morſel of Bread, and a ſmall draught of Wine without faith, and what can this do to the nouriſhing and ſtrengthning of our Souls? As the <hi>word profits not unleſs it be mixed with faith in thoſe that hear it,</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:35041:55"/>Heb. 4.2. So the Lord's Supper profits not unleſs mingled with faith in thoſe that receive it. It is true, were we only at this Ordinance to receive the Bread at the Miniſters hands that gives it, then there would be no ſuch need of Faith at this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. But at this Ordinance we are to take Chriſt out of God's hand, who is offered to us there, and this cannot be done without faith; were we only to eat the Bread and drink the Wine at this Supper, this might be done without faith, but we are to eat Chriſt's Fleſh and drink Chriſt's Blood, to ſeed upon a broken Crucified Saviour, who is not only the Maſter but the Matter of this feaſt, and this cannot be done but by faith. It is faith that feeds upon Chriſt, and derives virtue and vigour from him. <hi>His Fleſh is meat indeed and his Blood is drink indeed,</hi> John 6.55. Meat to be eaten not with the teeth but by faith. Meat indeed not in Nature but in Effect, becauſe it
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35041:55"/>nouriſheth the Soul, and gives E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life to them that eat thereof, v. 54. <hi>Whoſo eateth my Fleſh and drinketh my Blood hath Eternal life,</hi> &amp;c. Hath Eternal life, ay hath it already in a juſt Right and Title and ſhall have it in a certain actua Poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>There is great need of Faith, and Work for Faith in this Ordinance, to diſcern and ſpy out thoſe great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, that are wrapped up in the outward Elements. The want of which, <hi>viz.</hi> a right diſcerning of the Myſteries that are pointed at by theſe ſignes in this. Ordinance, is the cauſe of Perſons miſcarrying under it, is the cauſe of Perſons eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unworthily; and, as a conſequent of that, of their eating and drinking Damnation to themſelves; when Perſons in their eating and drinking at this Table, look no farther than at what preſents its ſelf to the eye of the Body. at the outward ſigns and Elements only, not diſcerning
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35041:56"/>the broken Body and the ſhed Blood of Chriſt, to be wrapped up in them, and repreſented by them; Putting no difference between the Sacramental Bread and Wine, and common bread and wine, putting no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and the body and blood of a meer Man. Between Bread Repreſenting the Body of Chriſt, and bread the ordinary ſtaff of Life: Between Wine, as repreſenting the Blood of Chriſt, and Wine that is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Cordial, and refreſhment to the natural Spirits. Why ſuch a perſon, when he cats and drinks at this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, eats and drinks unworthily, not diſcerning the Lord's Body. Eats the Bread, and drinks the Wine, but doth not cat the Body and Blood of Chriſt ſpiritually. And well may he be ſaid to eat and drink unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, becauſe by thus eating and drinking, he violates in thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Signs and Elements the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and regard due to the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35041:56"/>and Glory and Merit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Now Faith is that eye which pierceth through the Clouds and Shadows of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Signs and Elements, to thoſe Heavenly great and glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries in, and beyond them, even Chriſt's Body broken, and his Blood ſhed for us. Chriſt's Sweating drops of Blood in the Garden, and dying a Painful, Shameful, and Accurſed Death upon the Croſs. Faith eyes the great and wonderful Myſteries that are in this Death, and the great. Benefits ſlowing from thence to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Faith gives us a diſcerning of theſe things in the Supper; not a Speculative diſcerning, but a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Practical apprehenſion of them, ſuch as ſtirreth up ſutable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and holy Affections, as if we had ſeen him hang bleeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs, Sweating under that load and burden of Divine Wrath and Diſpleaſure due to the ſins of the Elect World which he bare, the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35041:57"/>leaſt of which would have broken the back of the Whole Creation to have ſtood under it. Many a Man may be able to Diſcourſe very well and underſtandingly about theſe Great Myſteries of the Supper: To tell what is the meaning of the Bread, and what the meaning of the Wine is, that have no Spiritual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, but is meerly the Fruit of an Hiſtorical Faith, or Tradition, that is current in the Age or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try he lives in. But Faith gives a Spiritual Diſcerning, ſuch a ſight and ſenſe of theſe great Myſteries, as doth impreſs an holy dread and a we upon the Soul, and an holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing and delighting in the Soul. So that upon this account we ſee what great need there is of Faith in our Receiving and Partaking of this Supper.</p>
                  <p>Again, There is great need of Faith, and work for Faith in this Ordinance, to reconcile us to the meanneſs and deſpicableneſs, as to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35041:57"/>outward appearance of this, as well as other Ordinances of Chriſt. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are ſimple in appearance, and therefore the Creature is ready to carp at them. It is a Saying of one, <hi>Nihil adeo offendit hominum mentes ac ſimplicitas divinorum ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> &amp;c. There is nothing doth ſo much offend the Minds of Men, as the Simplicity of God's Ordinances. As in Baptiſm, there is but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle common Water, And what can this do, to cleanſe the Soul from Sin? So in the Lord's Supper, there is but a little Morſel of. Bread, and a ſmall Draught of VVine, a poor Feaſt to a Carnal Man. Carnal and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reaſon is greatly prejudiced, ſtumbled, and offended at ſo mean and deſpicable an appearance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee the need of Faith, and the Great Work for Faith in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. How mean and deſpicable ſoever theſe may ſeem, as to out ward appearance, yet they are high and Myſterious Inſtruments of our Peace,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35041:58"/>Growth and Comfort. And altho' Carnal Senſe, and Corrupted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot ſee it, yet Faith doth. How mean ſoever, as to outward appearance, theſe may ſeem, yet Faith eyes the Inſtitution and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that goes along with them. And where the Inſtitutions of Chriſt are attended with his own Bleſſing, there Ordinances, though never ſo ſimple in appearance, yet ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come effectual for producing great Effects, and for obtaining high and glorious Ends.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly. There is great need of Faith, and Work for Faith in this Ordinance, for a real and cloſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of thoſe great Benefits and Myſteries that are repreſented to us, and diſcerned by us in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Faith is not only the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual eye of the Soul, whereby we diſcern Chriſt Crucifyed, and the Myſteries and Merits, and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his Death in this Supper,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35041:58"/>Vailed under the outward Signes and Ellements; but it is alſo the Spiritual hand of the Soul whereby we take Chriſt, his Merits and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits offered and tendered to us in this Supper, and apply to our own Souls benefit, comfort, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Of what advantage will the fineſt dainties be, that can poſſibly be provided, for nouriſhment and refreſhment, if not fed upon and digeſted by us? Or the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Medicine that ever was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, Of what advantage will it be to a Sick Perſon for Health and Recovery, if he do not take it and apply it? So, of no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail or advantage would Chriſt be, and all his excellent Benefits to us in this Ordinance, without a real and cloſe application of them to our own Souls; unleſs taken and received, fed upon, and digeſted; and this muſt be the work of Faith, to take and eat, to take and drink, VVhat? Bread and VVine only?
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35041:59"/>no: theſe are the leaſt matters, but Chriſt's Body and Blood alſo, and all the Benefits thereof, muſt, by Faith, be taken, and received, eaten, and digeſted to our Spiritual Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and growth in Grace. This may ſuffice to ſhew the great need that there is of Faith, and the great Work that there is for Faith, in our partaking of this Supper.</p>
                  <p>There is alſo great work for Faith after our receiving and partaking, and that is ſtedfaſtly to rely upon what Chriſt hath done and Suffered for us, upon his Righteouſneſs and Satisfaction, upon the efficacy and ſufficiency of his Death and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, of his Blood and Merit, all which have been in a moſt lively manner exhibited and repreſented to us in this Supper. And our work and buſineſs is to walk with a fiducial dependence upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in every act, and duty of worſhip, for acceſs to God for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from God. In every freſh
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35041:59"/>perplexity of Mind, doth Satan ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, Conſcience accuſe, the Law ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe? why yes it may be all theſe accuſe us, why then our work and buſineſs is to plead the fulneſs of Chriſt's ſatisfaction, and the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of his Merit againſt all theſe charges and accuſations, and here is enough in this Righteouſneſs and Satisfaction of Chriſt to anſwer all. And the great work of Faith is to rely and depend upon it. Under a freſh ſenſe and feeling of Guilt we are to have a recourſe to this blood of Chriſt, for the removal of it; and under the daily ſenſe and feeling of the working of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, inbred Corruption, we are to have a daily recourſe unto this blood of Chriſt, that it may be ſubdued: we are to eye the Death of Chriſt for sanctification, as well as for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification; for Mortification and killing of Luſt, as well as for the taking away and removal of Guilt. Alas, we are no more able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35041:60"/>our own Luſts, than we are to remove our own Guilt; but are as much beholden to Chriſt for the one as for the other. In a word, throughout the whole of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Race and Courſe, our eye muſt be unto Chriſt, <hi>Looking unto Jeſus, who is the Author and Finiſher of our Faith.</hi> Every day, by freſh acts of Faith, caſting and committing all the concernments of our Souls into the hands of our dear Redeemer. This is to walk fiducially, and thus we are to walk after this Supper. One end of which Supper was, for the ſtrengthening of Grace in our Souls; not only for the inflaming our Love, but for the ſtrengthning our Faith: Not only that our love to him might wax hotter and hotter, but that our Faith in him, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance upon him might be ſtronger and ſtronger.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="particular">
                  <p n="5">5. VVe muſt walk with a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hatred of, and indignation againſt ſin. VVe have been Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35041:60"/>a Crucifyed Bleeding Dying Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, And pray what was the occaſion of this ſhameful ignominious and Reproachful Death? Why it was ſin. But not any ſin of his own that he was brought to this Death and Sufferings, but for the ſins of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>The Lord laid upon him the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of his People,</hi> Iſa. 53. And there was not only an act of God the Father, in laying theſe ſins upon Chriſt, but there was alſo Chriſt's own voluntary conſent to take them upon him. So that it was ſin, the ſins of his Elect People, that he took upon him, which was the occaſion of his bitter Sufferings. <hi>He was wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our Tranſgreſſions, and bruiſed for our Iniquities;</hi> Ay, and theſe were far more wounding and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him than was the piercing of his natural Side with the Souldier's Spear. This was that which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd that Agony of Body and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of soul, even the Wrath and Diſpleaſure of God, manifeſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35041:61"/>the ſins which he bare. And who of us is able to conceive of that which he felt, of that Torment he felt in his Body, and of that Anguiſh he felt in his soul. <hi>My Soul,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is exceeding ſorrowful, even unto death;</hi> and upon the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fin muſt be an exceeding great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, which was the occaſion of ſo great Sufferings. And indeed there is no Glaſs doth ſo fully and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover to us the evil and heinous nature of ſin, as the Glaſs of Chriſts Death and Sufferings. Now, in this Supper Ordinance, we have a lively Repreſentation of a broken Crucifyed Chriſt, broken and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified for our ſins; his Body bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his Blood ſhed for our ſins; this is that which our Faith is to eye in our participation of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. Have we ſeen Chriſt in this Ordinance Broken and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, and bruiſed for our ſins, and ſhall we dare to live in ſin? Is this
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35041:61"/>a walk ſuteable and becoming thoſe that have been at the Table of the Lord? Suteable to thoſe expreſſions of Love that are manifeſted, or ſutea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe Myſteries that are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered there, or to thoſe great Benefits that are repreſented there? Surely no: After we have been at this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we come under deeper Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of abandoning and hating ſin than before. Have we received the Lord's Supper as a Seal of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſins, And ſhall we dare, after this Supper, to fall a-freſh into the Commiſſion of the ſame ſins? What is this but to prophane the Blood of the Covenant, and to trample under foot the Blood of the son of God? And is this our kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to our Friend? who ſo freely parted with his Life, and Hearts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood; Surely they greatly miſtake the nature and end of this Supper, that go from it with a purpoſe to return to their Vice and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and uſe it only for a Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35041:62"/>and Tolleration for their ſins. It is a ſure and certain ſign, that our hearts were never rightly, and truly humbled, and broken for ſin before we came to this supper, if there be any ſecret purpoſes, and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions kept up and maintained in our Souls of returning to our ſins after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. If it was neceſſary to bring bleeding hearts to this Ordinance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then certainly it is as neceſſary to carry away broken and bleeding hearts for ſin from it, eſpecially when we have had ſuch an affecting ſight preſented to us, <hi>viz.</hi> a Chriſt brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and broken for our ſins. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks every time we partake of this Ordinance, it ſhould ſtir up in us a greater abhorrency, and hatred of ſin than ever. O conſider what wrath our ſins did derive upon Chriſt, in order to the kindling our hatred and indignation againſt them. What ſhall we make light of that which Chriſt found ſo heavy and heinous, which fetched from him
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35041:62"/>ſuch great drops of Blood, and extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him ſo bitter and dreadful a Lamentation, <hi>My Soul,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is exceeding ſorrowful, even unto death;</hi> and upon the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Did Chriſt ſhed all his Hearts-blood for thy ſins, and doſt thou think much to ſhed a few Penitential Tears for them? Or wilt thou hug ſuch a Viper in thy boſom, which was ſuch a ſting in the heart of thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? Wilt thou pretend to have had Fellowſhip with Chriſt in this Ordinance, and afterward hold fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the unfruitful works of Darkneſs? What a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="particular">
                  <p>6. We muſt walk with a greater weanedneſs of affection from the World. <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>that I ſhould glory in any thing, ſave in the Croſs of Christ, by which the world is crucifyed to me, and I unto the world,</hi> Gal. 6.14. He was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſuch an holy indifferency, as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35041:63"/>to care no more for the World than the World cared for him, and this he did through the Croſs of Chriſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring how the World dealt with Chriſt, and how little he regarded the World. Now ſhall we who have been ſo lately Celebrating and Commemorating the Death and Crucifixion of Chriſt, love that, and cleave to that which dealt ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly by him, or eſteem that which was ſo little eſteemed by him? Is this a walk worthy of his Dying-Love? no: this is no way becoming thoſe that have been entertained at this Table. Therefore, where we ſee Perſons, after they have been at this Table, conforming to the World, to the Faſhions and Vanities thereof, their Hearts and Affections glued to the World, and the Things of the World, perſuing after it with the greateſt vehemency and eagerneſs, why this is ſuch a kind of walking as is no way ſuteable and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gueſts of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="particular">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:35041:63"/>
                  <p>7. We muſt walk with a more inflamed Love and endeared Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the bleſſed Lord Jeſus. This Supper-Ordinance is a Love-token betwixt Chriſt and his Church, where they mutually ſeal up their Affections to each other. In it we have had the higheſt and the fulleſt demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Love to us; <hi>Greater love than this hath no man, that a man lay down his life for his friends.</hi> VVhy ſuch love there was in the heart of Chriſt to poor finners, as to lay down his life for them. <hi>Hereby perceive we the love of God,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle <hi>John, becauſe he Laid down his life for us,</hi> 1 John 3.16. Ay, here was a full demonſtration of it indeed; This was a demonſtration of that love which was in the heart of Chriſt from Eternity to poor ſinners. O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Love that he ſhould open his Breaſt to receive into his own heart the ſharp point of that ſword which was directed againſt us. VVhere ſhall we find love to match this
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35041:64"/>love? Rather than we ſhould be Sacrifices to Divine Juſtice, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would become the Sacrifice. Have we had ſuch demonſtrations of his love repreſented to us in this Ordinance? O then with what an inflamed love, and endeared affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ought we to walk after this Ordinance of the Lord's Supper. As we are to hate ſin more, ſo we are to love Chriſt more. <hi>Let us therefore,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorts us, <hi>walk in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us, and given himſelf for us, an offering and ſacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour,</hi> Eph. 5.2. The moſt intenſe love, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt affections are due from us to Chriſt, who loved us, and dyed for us, and roſe again for our Juſtifyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and is gone before to prepare Manſions of Glory for the ſeeing God's Face, and enjoying God's Preſence to all Eternity. Theſe are endearing conſiderations, and ſhould mightily endear Chriſt to our Souls.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35041:64"/>And O that we could find and feel more of the conſtraining power and efficacy of this Love of Chriſt, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day drawing out our hearts and affections more after himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="particular">
                  <p>8. We are to walk more inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, that is to ſay, more upon the ſearch and enquiry, not ſo much into the affairs and concerns of others, as into the frames, and conditions, and affairs of our own Souls. Many are buſy in making their reflexions and obſervations upon others, and in the mean time overlook themſelves. The Mind hath many turnings, but the beſt is, when it turns in and reflects upon it ſelf. This was holy <hi>David</hi>'s way and practice, Pſal. 77.6. <hi>I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with my own heart, and my ſpirit made diligent ſearch.</hi> Ay, this is a commendable walk indeed, when we are much in communing with our own hearts, enquiring how mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters go there. As the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and careful Tradeſman is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten looking into his Accounts, that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35041:65"/>he may know how it is with him, whether he goes backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the World. So ſhould we be often looking into our hearts, that we may know how it is with us, whether we go backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in our Souls. That we may know what our loſſes have been, and what our gains have been. This is a walking that is pleaſing to God, as is evident from the many Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of his Word and Will to this purpoſe, Lament. 3.40. <hi>Let us ſearch and try our ways, and turn again unto the Lord,</hi> Hag. 1.5. <hi>Now therefore thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, conſider your ways.</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. <hi>Examine your ſelves, prove your own ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. In order to the preparing our hearts to approach the Lord's Table, the Apoſtle recommends to us this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent duty of Self-examination, 1 Cor. 11.28. <hi>But let a man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, and ſo let him eat,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle is here laying before them the ſin and danger of unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35041:65"/>participation of this Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, and gives them to underſtand, that ſuch as eat and drink unworthily, are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Body and Blood of the Lord. Here he lays before them the ſin. And in the 29th <hi>Verſe</hi> he lays before them the danger, and tells them plainly, that ſuch as eat and drink unworthily, eat and drink Damnation to themſelves. Now to prevent ſuch a miſchief as this, he recommends to them this excellent duty of Self-examination. It is as much as if he had ſaid, If ye would not eat and drink unworthily, and thereby eat and drink damnation to your ſelves, then ſet upon this buſineſs of Self-examination; <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Truly as this is neceſſary before we venture upon this Ordinance, ſo it is as neceſſary after we have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken of it. <hi>Let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo let him eat,</hi> &amp;c. So alſo let
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35041:66"/>a Man eat and drink, and ſo let him examine himſelf. An after reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is as neceſſary as a previous exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. We examine our ſelves before, in order to receive good. And we muſt examine our ſelves after to ſee what good we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. After our performance of any duty we ſhould be upon the enquiry what good we have got? This Queſtion we ſhould put to our ſelves, after every Prayer we make, after every Sermon we hear, after every time we Communicate, at the end of every Duty, and at the end of every day. We have been lately partaking of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lord's Supper, and as we are frequently exhorted to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelves before we ſit down at this Ordinance; So the Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now is to examine our ſelves after we are riſen from it. What Warmth of Affection had we in it? and not only ſo, But what Warmth of Affection do we now find remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35041:66"/>and abiding upon us? Is not that Heat and Warmth in a great meaſure abated, and loſt already? This is that which we ſhould look to, that we do not eaſily or quickly, after Duties are over, loſe that Heat and Warmth which we got in the Duty. at the end of every Duty, and at the end of every day, we are ſeriouſly and faithfully to examine, and conſider, what of God, and what of Chriſt hath been diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me this day, or in this or that Duty? VVhat diſcoveries have been made of our ſelves to our ſelves, of the baſeneſs and vileneſs and corruptions of our own hearts? VVhat expreſſions of love to God, and Chriſt? VVhat expreſſions of Sorrow for ſin? VVhat delight in Chriſt, and deſires after Chriſt have been working in my Soul this day? VVhat lively vigorous acts and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Grace hath been put forth, not only in the Duty performed, but ſince the Duty was performed?
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35041:67"/>VVhat Power hath been exerted this day, in a way of oppoſition and reſiſtance againſt Temptations, and againſt Corruptions? VVhat Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fildings and Apoſtacys, and defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from God have I been guilty of ſince the laſt time I renewed my Covenant? And what Sorrow and Contrition of heart hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed for it? VVhat guilt and defilement have I a-freſh contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and what application in a way of Faith of the Blood of Chriſt hath been made for pardon and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? VVhat growth and encreaſe of comfort and refreſhment and joy do I find in my Soul? VVhat en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſtrength do I find to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Dutys? To bear Afflictions? To reſiſt Temptations? To morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy Corruptions? To walk with God? Thus we ſhould be upon the enquiry every day, and after every Duty, and eſpecially after this Ordinance of the Lord's Supper. Is my Soul more knit to Chriſt, my
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35041:67"/>heart more raviſhed with his Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Excellency? Doth Chriſt appear more Fair, and Sin more foul to me than before? Chriſt more ſweet, and Sin more bitter? Sure I am it ought to be ſo with every one of us who have been Gueſts at our Lord's Table, where we might ſee Two affecting, heart-melting, heart-breaking ſights: The one was Chriſt broken for us. The other was Chriſt broken by us. A Chriſt broken for us, and there was an heart over<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>flowing with love, pitty, and compaſſion to us, which ſhould beget in us hearts glowing and burning, and flaming with love to him. And then we have ſeen a Chriſt broken by us, wounded and bruiſed, and pierced, and broken by our ſins, which were the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his bitter Agonies and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. Now as in the firſt we ſaw the fulneſs of Chriſts love, ſo in this we ſee the foulneſs of our ſins, that nothing but the blood of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35041:68"/>Chriſt can cleanſe us from it. There is nothing that repreſents to us the bitterneſs of ſin, like the Su<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erings of Chriſt. Theſe things have been lately in a moſt lively manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to us, and ſet before the eye and view of our Faith in this Supper-ordinance. But how have our Hearts and Souls been affected with theſe lights? Doth Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more fair, and Sin more foul than before, Chriſt more ſweet, and Sin more bitter? thus it ought to be with us who have been at this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lord's Supper. And our work and buſineſs now is to look to it, that indeed it be ſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="particular">
                  <p>9. More Couragiouſly and with greater reſolution for Chriſt. VVe that have had ſuch Tokens of Chriſts love, and ſuch Inſtances of his zeal and courage for our good, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the greateſt difficulties that lay in the way of our Salvation and Happineſs; not only the rage of Men, and Devils, but the VVrath of his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35041:68"/>Father too: How ſhould the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this arm and fill our Minds and Souls with an holy zeal and courage for him, 1 Pet. 4.1. <hi>For as much then as Christ ſuffered for us in the fleſh, arm your ſelves likewiſe with the ſame mind.</hi> At this Table of the Lord we have ſeen what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for us. It therefore concerns us to give a proof of our zeal and courage for him, by owning his ways, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his truths, by withſtanding Temptations, and turning a deaf ear to all the Sollicitations of the Fleſh, not betraying the Intereſt of Chriſt into the hands of Enemies, ſtanding our ground as long as we have ground to ſtand upon, ſuffering the loſs of all things, rather than part with Chriſt; Honours, Pleaſures, Preferments, Liberties, Livelyhoods, nay, Life it ſelf, rather than part with Chriſt. VVith ſuch a zeal for Chriſt was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Acts 21.13. <hi>What mean ye to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35041:69"/>weep, and break my heart? For I am ready not only to be bound, but to ſuffer at Jeruſalem for the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Where ſhall we find ſuch a bold Lyon-like ſpirited Man for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt again, as this bleſſed Apoſtle was. He feared neither Bonds nor Death; <hi>I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> ſays he, <hi>not only to be bound, but to ſuffer and dye at Jeruſalem for the ſake of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> rather than deny or diſown Chriſt. Neither the flatteries of the World on the one hand, ſhould entice him away, nor the frowns of the World on the other hand fright him away from Chriſt Such a zeal and courage for Chriſt ſhould our Minds be armed with, as to hold faſt the Profeſſion of our Faith without wavering in the view aud face of the greateſt oppoſition and difficulty that may be in our way to Heaven. A Chriſtian, of all Men, ſhould be armed with the greateſt Courage and Reſolution, becauſe he is like to meet with the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35041:69"/>ſoareſt and ſharpeſt Aſſaults. <hi>In the world ye ſhall have Tribulation,</hi> John 16. <hi>ult.</hi> Whilſt we are in this World we muſt not expect much eaſe or quiet; Storms and Tempeſts we muſt expect in our Voyage or Journey to Heaven. The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Life is a continual warfare. From our Spiritual birth to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural death; from the hour and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we did firſt ſet our face Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venward, till we come to ſet our foot in Heaven, we ſhall have trouble and moleſtation on one kind or another. There is no place which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can call Priviledged Ground. O then what need have we of Courage, to hold on, and hold out to the end. The Devil will never leave Tempting, nor the World Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring, nor the Fleſh Solliciting whilſt we are upon our March. The <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> you know, had no Peace till they lodged their Colours in <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Freſh Troubles and Difficulties did ariſe in their March from <hi>Aegypt</hi>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:35041:70"/>to <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo it will be with us in our March to Heaven. We muſt bear the Croſs before we wear the Crown, <hi>through much tribulation muſt enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of God,</hi> Acts 14.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="particular">
                  <p>10. With a more endeared love and affection one to another, Epheſ. 5.2. <hi>And walk in love as Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo loved us, and gave himſelf an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and a ſacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour.</hi> This is the Apoſtles Exhortation to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> viz. <hi>To walk in love.</hi> And the Argument by which he preſſeth this, is taken from the love of Chriſt to us, in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his Life, and offering up himſelf a Sacrifice to God for us. Now this Love we have been lately Celebrating and Commemorating in this Ordinance of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, where we have ſeen Chriſt broken and Crucifyed for us; And can we have a greater Motive to love one another than this, who have been Celebrating the love of Chriſt together. It highly concerns
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35041:70"/>every one of us to walk in love, <hi>as Christ alſo loved us, and hath given himſelf for us.</hi> But here it may be asked, what is it to walk in love? Why to walk in love, <hi>Non eſt ſimpliciter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere, ſed totam vitam in Charitate tranſigere.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zanch.</hi> inlo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Not ſimply to love, but to paſs our whole life in love; <hi>Ita ut omnia a Charitate ſlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, &amp; in Charitate fiant, &amp; in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem deſinant:</hi> So that all may flow from love, and may be done in love, and may end in love. This is to walk in love; and ſo ought we to walk in love one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Performing all Offices of love and kindneſs, and reſpect one towards another, pittying and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one for another. Admoniſhing and reproving one another in love and meekneſs. Bearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burdens, aſſiſting and helping one another, kind. and tender-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one to another, forbearing and forgiving one another, even as God
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35041:71"/>for Chriſt's-ſake hath forgiven us. All bitterneſs, and anger, and wrath and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put away from us, with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</p>
                  <p>Indeed it is much to be lamented and bewailed, that there ſhould be ſuch heats and diviſions, and animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, ſuch anger and clamour, and evil-ſpeaking, and I wiſh I could not ſay malice too, amongſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Church-members. Is this a walk any way ſuteable, or becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the expreſſions of Chriſt's love in dying and bleeding for us? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no. O how contrary is this to a Goſpel ſpirit, which is a Spirit of Love, and meekneſs. What, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Body, and mutual Members, members one of another, and ſhall we not own one another, embrace one another, be cordially affected <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zanch.</hi> inlo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> each to other? What, Members one of another, and yet carry it with that ſtrangeneſs, and diſtance, and diſaffection, as if we
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35041:71"/>ſtood in no relation at all one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? What never agree but juſt when we are under the laſh, juſt under the Rod? How juſt is it with God to bring us into our former ſtraits and difficulties again? that we may learn to love one another better, that there may be a greater harmony and agreement amongſt us. There never was more need of ſuch a Prayer as the Apoſtle put up for the <hi>Theſalonians,</hi> than now, <hi>The Lord make you to abound in love one towards another,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12. I ſay, a Prayer never more needful ſince Chriſt had a Church upon Earth, than it is in this day amongſt us in this Nation, where love amongſt Brethren was never at a lower Ebb. Divided heads have made divided hearts. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in Judgment hath made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in love and Affection, ſo that the love of many is waxed cold. Now the good Lord who only can make dry bones to live, revive this Affection where it is dead or dying,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:35041:72"/>and confirm it where it yet continues, that being thus Members of Chriſt and Members one of another, we may fulfil that great and everlaſting Commandment, that as it hath been taught from the beginning. of the World, ſo it is to be practiſed to the end of the ſame, yea even to Eternity, that we love one another, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.11. This is that we are moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently exhorted to, Heb. 13.1. <hi>Let brotherly love continue.</hi> Rom. 12.9, 10. <hi>Let love be without diſſimulation, be kindly affectioned one towards another with brotherly love,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.8. <hi>Finaly brethren be ye all of one mind, having compaſſion one of another,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.23. And in many other places. This is that which as it is the bond of all Chriſtian Virtues, ſo it is the bond of all Chriſtian Societys, in both which reſpects it is called the bond of Perfectneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. A moſt perfect bond knitting and uniteing hearts together, which no other bond can do, and being ſo it is in the firſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35041:72"/>place to be put on by all thoſe who would joyne themſelves to the Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>above all things,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>put on Charity which is the bond of perfectneſs.</hi> This alſo is laid down for a mark and character of Chriſt's Sheep and Diſciples, and laid down by Chriſt himſelf. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples if ye love one another,</hi> John 13.35. This is that which is ſo highly applauded and commended in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Pſal. 133.1. <hi>Behold how good aud pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity.</hi> And where this is kept up and maintained even there the Lord commands the Bleſſing even life for evermore. Now by all this it appears that to walk in love is a very ſuteable and becoming walk, eſpecially after this Supper of the Lord, which indeed is a Sacramental ſeal and token not only of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, but alſo of our communion with his Members, of our fellowſhip with the Saints, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35041:73"/>of our communion and fellowſhip one with another. This the Apoſtle clearly intimates, 1 Cor. 10.16, 17. <hi>For we,</hi> ſays he, <hi>being many are one bread, and one body, for we are all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that one bread.</hi> This Supper as it is a bond of our union and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, ſo it is a bond of our union and communion one with another as his Members. Therefore every time we partake of it we ſhould be more and more, faſter and faſter knit in love and affection one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This is a confirming Ordinance, and as it is to confirm and inflame our love to Chriſt, ſo it is to confirm and inflame our love one to another.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="particular">
                  <p>11. After this Ordinance we are to walk more chearfully and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably. Of all perſons Believers have moſt reaſon to be chearful and joyful at all times and in all conditions, in times of Adverſity as well as in times of Proſperity, tho' he feeds upon Bread and Water yet he hath greater reaſon to rejoyce than the greateſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35041:73"/>Monarch in the World. I do not ſay a Believer always walks joyfully and chearfully, no, ſometimes he walks dejectedly. Tho a child of light yet ſometimes he walks in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but yet I ſay a Believer hath moſt reaſon to walk joyfully and chearfully, and it is his duty ſo to do and hath frequent calls and exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to it, Phil. 3.1. <hi>Finally my brethren rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Phil. 4.4. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord always and again I ſay rejoyce.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.16. <hi>Rejoyce ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Now a Believer hath evermore matter of rejoyceing, and reaſon to rejoyce, inaſmuch as all that which is really matter of dejection is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and taken away, <hi>viz.</hi> the guilt of Sin and the Curſe of the Law, and the Wrath of God, now theſe are all removed and taken away by Chriſt who came to procure peace by the Blood of his Croſs, and in whom we have Redemption thro his Blood. A Believer hath evermore matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceing, upon the account of that
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35041:74"/>fulneſs that is treaſured up in Chriſt, in whom it pleaſed the Father that all fulneſs ſhould dwell, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. Now what is there that a poor creature can deſire or ſtand in need of in order to the making him compleatly happy and bleſſed but what may be found in this All-fulneſs of Chriſt. Here is wiſdom for his Direction and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, included in it. Here is a compleat Righteouſneſs for his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Here is Grace and Holineſs for his Sanctification. Righteouſneſs to give him a Right and Title to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Grace and Holineſs to give him a meetneſs and fitneſs for Heaven, and power and ability to bring him ſafe thether; upon theſe conſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others a Believer hath always ground and matter of rejoyceing; And by this they are deſcribed as by their vital act, Phil. 3.3. <hi>We are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the Fleſh.</hi> A Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever ſhould rejoyce always, walk
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35041:74"/>joyfully and chearfully at all times, and eſpecially after Sacrament ſeaſons, when he hath been renewing his Covenant with God. God a freſh making over himſelf and his all to the Believer, giving him a freſh ſenſe and ſeal of his love and the pardon of his Sins when Chriſt with all his Benefits and Purchaſes and Merit, Chriſt in all his Offices, Chriſt in all his Grace and fulneſs hath been afreſh made over to him. His Blood in all the virtue and efficacy of it ſealed and applyed to the Believers. The new Teſtament with all its Promiſes and Priviledges and Benefits thereof, this is all ratified and confirmed in the Blood of Chriſt to the Believer, and aſſured to him in this Supper-Ordinance. They who have been entertained at this Goſpel Feaſt who have been feeding upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of God's Grace, and have received freſh Tokens and Pledges of his Love; for ſuch to walk de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectedly, and Mournfully, reflects
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35041:75"/>great diſhonour, and highly affronts the Maſter of the Feaſt, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſparageth the Matter of it too; it is a great undervaluing of Chriſt and his Blood, as if the guilt or filth of thy ſin did exceed the Merit of his Blood, or was too great for his Blood to remove and cleanſe. After this Ordinance we are to walk more joyfully and chearfully, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the Lord, and joying in the God of our Salvation. We ſhould go home to our Houſes and Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Rejoycing; and go on our way, through this Pilgrimage, with Joy, as the Eunuch, when Baptiſed, did, it is ſaid, <hi>He went on his way rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> Acts 8.39. So ſhould we, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we have been at this Supper, go on our way, through this World Rejoycing, ſaying to our Souls, as <hi>David</hi> did to his, <hi>Return to thy reſt O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:35041:75"/>
               <div n="12" type="particular">
                  <p>12. With more earneſt Breathings and Longings of Soul after freſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. It is not a little of the World that will ſatisfy a Covetous Man; nor a little Pleaſure that will ſatisfy a Carnal Voluptuous Mind; Nor a little Honour and Preferment, that will ſatisfy an Ambitious Aſpiring Mind. Nor is it a little of Chriſt that will ſatisfy a Gracious Renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heart. See how <hi>David</hi> thirſted after God, Pſal. 63.1, 2. <hi>O God, thou art my God, early will I ſeek thee, my Soul thirſteth for thee, my fleſh long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for thee in a dry land where no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, to ſee thy power and thy glory as I have ſeen thee in the Sanctuary. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had taſted of the Sweet of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment and Communion with God, and this ſets his Soul a longing and thirſting, and breathing after more of God, Pſal. 42.1, 2. <hi>As the Hart panteth after the Water-brooks, ſo pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my Soul after God; my Soul thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35041:76"/>for the living God, when ſhall I come and appear before thee?</hi> The like breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of soul we find after Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, in Pſal. 84.1, 10. <hi>How amiable are thy Tabernacles O Lord of Hoſts, my Soul longeth, yea even faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the Courts of the Lord; my heart and my fleſh cryeth out for the living God. For a day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand: I had rather be a door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper in the Houſe of my God, than to dwell in the Tents of Wickedneſs.</hi> Such breathings and longings of Soul after Communion with Chriſt ſhould be kept up and maintained in our Souls after every time we partake of this bleſſed Ordinance. Have we this day ſat down under the ſhadow of Chriſt, and hath his fruit been ſweet and pleaſant to our taſte? Have we had any taſte of the Grace and Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt at his Table? Have our Souls been filled as with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſs, delighted and ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with Communion with Chriſt? Have we met this day with any
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:35041:76"/>freſh aſſurances of the love of God in Chriſt to our Souls, of the pardon of our ſins in the precious blood of Chriſt? Hath there been any freſh life, and vigour, and grace commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated from Chriſt our everlaſting head to our Souls this day? Have we been fed with hidden Manna, with the Bread and Water of Life? Have we ſeen any thing of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Glory of Chriſt at his own Table? O then how ſhould we be breathing and longing after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of ſuch ſeaſons and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities as theſe are? O when will this Supper return? When ſhall I come and appear before thee? O that I might ſtill be feaſting my Soul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe dainties. Thus we ſhould be walking with more earneſt breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Soul after freſh Communion with Chriſt, not only in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but in all other Ordinances of Divine Worſhip, and not only ſo, but long to be for ever with him, after compleat enjoyment of him in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35041:77"/>Heaven above. If it be ſo ſweet to enjoy him in Ordinances here, O what will it be, nay, How far ſweeter will it be to enjoy him in Heaven, where we ſhall enjoy him freely, fully, famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly and eternally, without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption or intermiſſion. Thus we have ſeen how we are to walk after this Supper Ordinance; and, that we may thus walk, it is neceſſary that we be ſtrengthned with all might, according to the glorious power of God. The Devil to be ſure will be oppoſing, with all his might, ſuch a walk as this; and our own wicked, baſe, deceitful, treacherous hearts will be too ready to ſide and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with him: Therefore, that ſuch a walk may be kept up, and maintained, that we may walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Lord, unto all pleaſing, it is neceſſary that we be ſtrengthned with all might, according to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious power, 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 11. Let us therefore be often diſpatching a cry to Heaven for that ſtrength and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:35041:77"/>whereby we may be enabled to maintain ſuch a walk, and daily depend upon Chriſt for ſtrength, in whom we have not only Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ſtrength too. That through daily Communications of Grace and Strength from him, we may be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſo to live, and act, and walk, whilſt we are here, that we may fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Courſe with joy, and, at laſt, an entrance, yea, an abundant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, an entrance with joy and triumph, may be adminiſtred to us into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that from his Kingdom of Grace, we may be received into his Kingdom of Glory; and from the proviſions of Grace we may be taken to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of Glory, and ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> at an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Feaſt, eat and drink at Chriſt's Table in Chriſt's Kingdom. Now whoſo is wiſe and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the Loving-kindneſs of the Lord:
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35041:78"/>They ſhall go from ſtrength to ſtrength, their Souls ſhall be fat and flouriſhing, and made to encreaſe with the encreaſes of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35041:78"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
